మీకు ఏదైనా వీడియో కోసం ఉపశీర్షికలు కావాలా?
-==-
(మనోహరమైన సంగీతం ప్లే)
(సంగీతం వికసిస్తుంది)
(SQUAWKING)
- (కీటకాలు మరియు పక్షుల కిలకిలారావాలు)
- (జంతువులు దూరం నుండి పిలుస్తున్నాయి)
జేక్: పండోర అడవులు
చాలా నష్టాలను కలిగి ఉండండి.
(సస్పెన్స్‌ఫుల్ మ్యూజిక్ ప్లే)
(భారీగా ఊపిరి పీల్చుకోవడం)
కానీ అత్యంత ప్రమాదకరమైన విషయం
పండోర గురించి...
అంటే మీరు ఎదగవచ్చు
మీరు ఆమెను ఎక్కువగా ప్రేమించవచ్చు.
(GRUNTS)
(నవిలో పాడటం)
గుర్తుంచుకోవడానికి . మేము పాటలను పాడతాము
పూసకు,
మన జీవితంలో ఒక కథ.
ನಮ್ಮ ಮಗನ ಜನನಕ್ಕೆ ಒಂದು ಮಣಿ.
(ವಿಸ್ಮಯದಲ್ಲಿ ಗಾಸ್ಪ್ಸ್)
- ನೆಟೆಯಂ!
- (ಬೇಬಿ ಸ್ಕ್ವೀಲ್ಸ್)
ನಾವಿ ಜನರು: ನೆಟೆಯಂ!
(CONTINUES SINGING IN NA'VI)
JAKE: A bead
when we adopted
our daughter, Kiri.
Born of Grace's avatar.
A daughter whose conception
was a total mystery.
(BABIES GURGLING)
(SIGHS IN AWE)
(NEYTIRI CONTINUES
SINGING IN NA'VI)
A bead
for the first communion
with Eywa.
(ALL SINGING IN NA'VI)
The People say
we live in Eywa...
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
...and Eywa
lives in us.
The Great Mother
holds all her children
in her heart.
(CONTINUES SINGING IN NA'VI)
- (CHILD SQUEALS, LAUGHS)
- (SPEAKING NA'VI)
Happiness is simple.
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
(SHOUTS PLAYFULLY)
But who would've thought
a jarhead like me
could crack the code?
- (ROARS, SPEAKS NA'VI)
- (CHILDREN SCREAMING)
(IN NA'VI)
(ALL LAUGHING)
JAKE: (IN ENGLISH)
Before I knew it, we had four.
(DIREHORSE GRUNTS)
When we sent the Sky People
back to Earth,
a few of 'em stayed.
Science guys,
loyal to the Na'vi.
And then there was Spider.
- WOMAN: Spider, Spider...
- Spider!
JAKE: He was just stuck here.
Too young for a cryo-capsule.
- You little wild man.
- (YOUNG SPIDER GIGGLES)
YOUNG SPIDER: See you, Norm!
JAKE: Orphaned by the war,
he was raised by the lab guys.
Spider, take your spare!
I'm just going to the village!
JAKE: He wasn't
part of our family.
He was like a stray cat.
Just always around.
(ALL SPEAKING NA'VI)
Inseparable from our kids.
- (HISSES)
- (ALL SPEAKING NA'VI)
To Neytiri,
he would always be alien.
One of them.
(IN NA'VI)
(YOUNG SPIDER HOLLERS, YELLS)
(BOY GRUNTS)
JAKE: (IN ENGLISH) Took a few
years to get the language
through my thick skull.
JAKE: But now when I hear it,
it might as well be English.
I hate you!
Well, I hate you
times infinity, Lo'ak!
Penis face!
- (SCREAMS)
- Hey! Hey! That's enough.
Don't make me come over there.
(WHISPERING)
He's gonna come out
from behind those big rocks.
There he is.
There you go.
Go get it!
Yeah!
(CHUCKLES) Hey, Neteyam,
the mighty fisherman.
There you go. Good boy.
(CHUCKLES GLEEFULLY)
Wow.
Wow, that's a big one.
By the rocks. (GRUNTS)
Right where you said.
How tall is he?
- JAKE: He's... that tall.
- YOUNG LO'AK: He's tall!
JAKE: Goes by
too fast.
Like a dream.
(ALL LAUGH)
- NEYTIRI: Kiri.
- LO'AK: Bro, come on.
Come on.
Smile, skxawng.
- (CAMERA CLICKS)
- JAKE: Happiness is simple.
(NEYTIRI WHOOPS, GIGGLES)
- Like date night.
- (NEYTIRI YIPPING)
Time away from the kids.
(JAKE YIPPING)
(ENCHANTING MUSIC PLAYING)
(CHUCKLES)
(JAKE CHUCKLES)
(JAKE YIPPING)
(CHUCKLES, YIPS)
(JAKE GRUNTS)
(BOTH WHOOPING)
- (NEYTIRI YIPPING)
- (JAKE LAUGHS)
BOTH: Whoo!
JAKE: But the thing
about happiness...
it can vanish in a heartbeat.
(JAKE BREATHES HEAVILY)
A new star in the night.
It could only mean one thing.
(BREATHES HEAVILY)
(OMINOUS MUSIC PLAYS)
Ships. Decelerating.
And Sky People returning.
(OMINOUS MUSIC CONTINUES)
(RUMBLING)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(ANIMALS SHRIEKING)
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(ALL PANTING)
(ANIMALS CRYING)
- (NEYTIRI GASPING HEAVILY)
- (JAKE WHISPERS INDISTINCTLY)
(WEEPING)
(GRIM MUSIC PLAYS)
(HEAVY BREATHING THROUGH MASK)
WOMAN: Pulse 168.
He's coming up...
MAN: Yeah, here it comes.
WOMAN: You're just fine.
(ECHOES)
Just lie still.
Stay calm.
Yep. Pupillary reflex is good.
MAN 2: Get that out
of his face.
- MAN: Hey!
- Colonel,
can you hear me?
Colonel?
(GRUNTS)
WOMAN: You need
to lie back down, sir.
(GROWLING)
Sedate him!
Get outta here!
Go, go, go!
WOMAN: Get security!
- Grab him!
- (YELLS)
- WAINFLEET: Hold him!
- (GRUNTS)
- Calm down!
WAINFLEET: Colonel,
stand down!
Colonel, it's me!
Corporal Wainfleet!
(SNARLS)
(EXHALES DEEPLY)
Lyle?
That you?
Yes, sir.
And Z Dog.
And Fike.
(FIKE GRUNTS)
I'm all right.
Let me go.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(PENSIVE MUSIC PLAYING)
(SNARLS)
(GRUNTS)
Well...
ain't this a bitch.
(PENSIVE MUSIC CONTINUES)
ANNOUNCER: Stand by. Two
minutes to Pandora insertion.
Secure for Delta V.
MAN 1: All right.
Umbilical's clear.
MAN 2: Pulse ox 89.
In case you haven't
figured it out yet,
you're Colonel Miles Quaritch.
Only younger, taller, bluer,
and not nearly as good-lookin'.
In two hours, I fly a mission
against the Na'vi's stronghold.
The powers that be
thought it prudent
that I do this backup
just in case.
And if you are
watchin' it, well,
it means that I did get
my ticket punched.
(CLEARS THROAT) Hey, Parker,
just what the hell am I
supposed to say now?
Just remind him how this works.
- Who?
- Here.
So see this?
This is all your memories
- and your personality.
- Right.
We're gonna send this
back to Earth...
All right, I got it.
...where you're growing
in a lab as we speak.
We're gonna imprint you
with it, and then...
I got... Hey, hey, hey.
Am I doin' this,
or are you doin' this?
Hurry it up.
Anyway, the idea
is to get the minds of the
saltiest on-world operators.
Yeah, like Corporal Wainfleet
over there...
(GRUNTS DRAMATICALLY)
...and your
humble narrator into...
Oorah.
...recombinant bodies.
You're a recom now, Colonel,
loaded with my memories
and my charm.
What you won't remember
is my death
because it hasn't happened yet,
and it ain't gonna.
- WAINFLEET: Damn right.
- ZDINARSIK: Hell yeah.
Well, whatever happened,
if you're any clone of mine,
you'll be lookin'
for some payback.
And Jake Sully would be
at the top of that list.
(EXHALES HEAVILY)
Remember, kid,
a Marine can't be defeated.
Oh, you can kill us,
but we'll just regroup in hell.
Oorah.
Semper fi.
(CAMERA BEEPS)
- (TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
- (IKRAN ROARS)
(HOOTING)
(ULULATING)
(IKRAN SQUAWKING)
Ground team, go!
(WARRIORS SHOUTING WAR CRIES)
(WHEELS SCREECH)
(HEROIC MUSIC PLAYING)
(YELLS)
(WHOOPING)
(NEYTIRI ULULATING)
(YELLS)
- (GRUNTS)
- (PILOT GROANS)
(HOLLERS)
(ALL ULULATING)
(ULULATING)
TARSEM: Take this! Go!
(IKRAN SCREECHING)
Let's go. Two minutes, people.
Let's go.
Bro, we have got
to get down there.
No way!
Dad will skin us!
Come on.
Don't be a wuss.
Lo'ak!
Get back here, you...
Argh!
NORM: Taking the whole case!
We're taking mags,
the RPGs, the stingers.
(IKRAN SQUAWKS)
- Bro, let's go. Come on!
- NETEYAM: Lo'ak!
LO'AK: Okay, let's go!
Lo'ak!
TARSEM: Move! Take that!
Take these weapons.
Here, boy. Go!
- NETEYAM: Lo'ak!
- (ULULATING)
You don't even know
how to use it.
Dad taught me.
(WARRIORS HOLLERING)
(NA'VI SPOTTER SNARLS)
(NA'VI SPOTTER HOLLERS)
Gunship's inbound!
Fall back!
(GASPS)
(WARRIORS SHOUTING WAR CRIES)
LO'AK: Bro, come on!
(GRUNTS)
(HOLLERS)
JAKE: Lo'ak, where are you?
Neteyam!
Easy, easy, you okay?
- Yeah.
- Where's your brother?
- That way.
- Where is he? Where?
Get outta here! Go on!
Neteyam!
Oh, no.
Oh, no, no, no.
Oh, God.
(GROANS)
Dad?
- (JAKE GRUNTS)
- (CHOKING)
What are you doin' here, boy?
What the hell were you thinkin'?
I'm s... I'm sorry.
I'm sorry, sir.
QUARITCH: We are not
in Kansas anymore.
We are going to Pandora.
Now,
I know you're all askin'
yourselves the same question.
Why so blue?
(ALL LAUGH)
For our sins in our past life,
we have been brought back
in the form of our enemy.
That gives us their size,
their strength, their speed.
And with our training,
that's a pretty potent mix.
(WAINFLEET SNIFFS)
Do we have a mission yet?
Indeed we do.
Our mission is to
hunt down and kill
the leader of
the Na'vi insurgency.
The one they call Toruk Makto.
Jake Sully.
SQUAD: Yeah!
That's what it is!
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
(IKRAN SCREECHING)
Attack, attack!
Got ya!
- Tuk! Come on!
- Hyah!
I'm definitely faster
when I'm blue.
(LAUGHS) Skxawng.
No, seriously.
And the animals respect me more.
They don't think of me as human.
Wait.
You're human?
- Ha-ha.
- (GRUNTS)
(IKRAN SCREECHING)
(JAKE ULULATES)
- (CONCH BLOWS)
- TUK: Whoosh!
(WARRIORS ULULATING)
TUK: They're coming!
(WARRIORS YIPPING)
They're coming!
Kiri, Spider!
The war party's coming back!
Come on, come on.
KIRI: Let's go,
come on.
(WARRIORS YIPPING)
(SQUAWKS)
- (ROARS)
- (NEYTIRI GRUNTS)
- TUK: Mom!
- Tuk...
- Mom.
- Tuk, Tuk, Tuk, Tuk, Tuk.
Fall in.
You're supposed to be spotters.
You spot bogeys,
and you call 'em in.
From a distance!
Does any of this
sound familiar? Get here!
Jesus. I let you two geniuses
fly a mission,
and you disobey direct orders.
Kiri, can you go help
your grandmother
with the wounded? Please?
My brother is wounded.
- It's fine.
- JAKE: Baby girl, please.
- Tuk, go with her. Go.
- NETEYAM: Dad.
- Sir. I take full responsibility.
- (KIRI AND TUK SIGH)
JAKE: Yeah, you do.
That's right.
'Cause you're the older brother.
You gotta act like it.
NEYTIRI: MaJake.
Your son is actually bleeding.
Mother, it's fine. I...
Just go and get patched up.
Go on, dismissed.
You do understand
that you almost
got your brother killed.
Yes, sir.
You're grounded.
No flying for a month.
Now, see to the ikran.
All of 'em.
Yes, sir.
And get that crap off your face.
(IKRAN SCREECHING)
(SIGHS)
NETEYAM: (WINCES) Ow. Ow!
SPIDER: Aw, want a kiss
on the boo-boo?
- Give him this.
- Okay.
I would use yalna bark.
Here, drink.
Oh, you would?
And who is Tsahik?
You are, Grand... Move!
You are, Grandmother.
But yalna bark is better.
Ow, ow! Ow.
It stings less.
LO'AK: Mighty Warrior.
What? (SIGHS)
Neteyam and Lo'ak
try to live up to you.
It is very hard on them.
I know.
You are very hard on them.
I'm their father.
It's my job.
This is not a squad.
It is a family.
(JAKE SIGHS)
(WHISPERS)
I thought we'd lost them.
(SIGHS SOFTLY)
JOCELYN: We'll check
on this tomorrow.
Hey, man.
How's it going?
Hey, Spider.
Your ass is mine.
I'm right here.
- SPIDER: What's up, bro?
- MAN: What up?
JOCELYN: Avatars only,
go around!
- (KIRI MIMICS MOCKINGLY)
- Sorry.
Yeah. Those blue stripes don't
make you any bigger, bro.
- (KIRI CHUCKLES)
- SPIDER: Yeah, well,
I can still kick your ass.
(MACHINE WHIRRING)
- NORM: Oof! Hell of a day.
- (MAX CHUCKLES)
- MAX: Long run.
- (GRUNTING)
KIRI: Like a little
annoying bug.
- (LAUGHTER)
- Ha-ha. Real hysterical, guys.
You know what
really sucks though?
Is you can breathe
Earth air for hours,
and I can only breathe your
air for, like, 10 seconds.
Yeah, Monkey Boy,
that really sucks.
For you. (CHUCKLES)
Oh!
(SNARLS)
- Hi, Max.
- MAX: Hey, kids.
- Hey. What's up, Max?
- What up?
- SPIDER: What's up, Norm?
- Lo'ak.
Hi, Ma.
(DREAMY MUSIC PLAYING)
Maybe I'm just
losing it out here,
but I'm seeing real evidence
of a systemic response
on a global level.
I can't...
I won't use the term
"intelligence." It's, um...
(HEAVY BREATHING
THROUGH MASK)
...maybe "awareness"
is a better word.
It's like the entire
biosphere of Pandora
is aware...
and capable of
this cognitive response.
Oh, crap, I can't say that.
They'll crucify me.
I mean, I need
to say something that'll...
So who do you think
knocked her up?
- (CHUCKLING)
- Pretty sure it was Norm.
Totally.
You do not deserve to live.
No, no, no.
Think about it, right?
I mean, he's the teacher's pet.
He's out at the lab
with her all the time.
I would kill myself.
I would drink acid.
Bro, you're right.
He's, like, in every shot.
(CHUCKLING) Bro, look, look,
he's giving her looks.
Hey.
LO'AK: See, I'm thinkin'
their two avatars were out
in the woods all alone...
- Gross!
- (LO'AK LAUGHS)
Guys. I mean,
sometimes it's not so great
to know who your father was.
(SOLEMN MUSIC PLAYING)
Whatever.
Don't even remember him.
No, Spider.
- Dude.
- Spider...
You are not him.
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(HEAVY BREATHING
THROUGH MASKS)
(ENGINE ROARING)
CREW CHIEF: Go, go, go!
Directly inside the terminal.
Do not stop.
Move!
- (BREATHES DEEPLY)
- Masks off.
Sir,
this is the General.
(GENERAL GRUNTING)
(CONTINUES GRUNTING)
(PANTING)
General Ardmore.
- Good to meet you, Colonel.
- Hmm.
I've heard good things,
but a lot's changed
since your last tour here.
Walk with me.
(ROBOTS CHITTERING)
GENERAL ARDMORE: The new
ops center is over here.
That just came online.
These Swarm Assemblers,
they can put up a building
in six days.
We have done more here in a year
than in the previous 30 years.
We're not here to
run a mine, Colonel.
As On-World Commander,
I have been charged
with a greater mission.
(MACHINES WHIRRING LOUDLY)
Earth is dying.
Our task here
is to tame this frontier.
Nothing less than
to make Pandora
the new home for humanity.
But before we can do that,
we need to pacify the hostiles.
Sully's raids are becoming
bolder and more frequent.
His strikes are well-planned.
He's got tight coordination
between his ground
and air assets.
His forces are hitting
our outlying sites.
The mines, pipelines,
cutting off our supply chain.
And they hit a maglev
two days ago.
Any intel on Sully's
base of operations?
Yeah.
Give me the mountains.
It's a cave system
in the Hallelujah Mountains
somewhere.
But every time we send
our forces up there,
we take losses.
Our hardware really
stirs up the hornet's nest.
We only get 10 minutes
in enemy airspace,
they are all over us.
(INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER)
Colonel,
we believe your Blue Team
will be perceived as indigenous
and will not trigger
the immune response.
And how might we test
that hypothesis, General?
The hard way.
Outstanding.
(ENTHRALLING MUSIC PLAYING)
PILOT: We're entering
hostile airspace.
QUARITCH: Copy that.
(LAUGHS)
(ALL SHOUTING EXCITEDLY)
KIRI: Go! Whoo!
- SPIDER: Whoo!
- LO'AK: Whoa, bro!
- SPIDER: Uh-huh.
- KIRI: Go, Monkey Boy!
TUK: Guys, wait up!
(BIRDS AND INSECTS CHIRPING)
(ANIMALS CALLING IN DISTANCE)
(DISTANT SQUAWKING)
(TUK PANTING)
(CHUCKLES)
Tuk!
Keep up!
TUK: Okay, okay.
SPIDER: Bro, why'd
you bring her anyway?
She's such a cry baby.
She's all, "I'm telling.
"You're not supposed
to go to the battlefield.
"I'll tell Mom
if you don't let me come."
- Don't pick on her.
- (TUK JEERING)
LO'AK: Come on.
SPIDER: Oh, sick!
TUK: Are there
any dead bodies up there?
LO'AK: Bro, check it out.
Come on.
(INSECTS AND BIRDS CHIRPING)
(GASPS IN AWE)
- (WINGS FLUTTERING)
- (DREAMY MUSIC PLAYING)
(INSECT CROAKS AND CHIRPS)
(EXHALES CONTENTEDLY)
(INSECT BUZZING)
- (ANIMAL CHITTERS)
- (ZDINARSIK GASPS)
(BOTH CHITTERING)
(SCOFFS) No shit.
(DREAMY MUSIC PLAYING)
SPIDER: Kiri.
Kiri.
Kiri...
Kiri, hey.
- Hey.
- (KIRI MOANS SOFTLY)
Kiri.
(KIRI GRUNTS SOFTLY)
- (KIRI EXHALES)
- Are you okay?
(PANTING)
I was doing that thing again,
wasn't I?
Yeah, you were.
- TUK: Kiri!
- LO'AK: Kiri!
TUK: Kiri,
we have to get back.
SPIDER: All right, come on.
KIRI: What is it?
TUK: We're always
supposed to be home
by eclipse.
It's way too big for a human.
- Avatars?
- Maybe,
but they're for sure not ours.
What are you doing?
Shh, I'm tracking.
(UNEASY MUSIC PLAYING)
Watch your six.
ZDINARSIK: Clear.
Perimeter up.
Damn.
KIRI: We are never
supposed to come here.
(WHISPERING)
Dad is going to ground you.
(WHISPERING) Shh.
Can you stop?
For life.
Bro, we have got
to check this out.
Let's go.
Bro,
that's where your dad and my dad
fought.
That's your dad's actual suit.
- (CHUCKLES IN DISBELIEF)
- Holy shit.
Lyle, see if you can
pull some data
off that dash cam.
WAINFLEET: That thing's
deader than shit, Colonel.
- QUARITCH: So were we.
- WAINFLEET: All right.
I gotta call this in.
No, bro, we're gonna
get in trouble.
- Let's go.
- (GRUNTS)
(SQUAWKS)
LO'AK: (ON COMMS)
Devil Dog, Devil Dog,
this is Eagle Eye, over.
Eagle Eye.
Send your traffic.
I got eyes on some guys.
They look like avatars,
but they're in full camo
and carrying ARs.
There's six of them.
Over.
What's your pos?
Oh... We're at the old shack.
(SPIDER SIGHS)
Who's "we"?
Me, Spider, Kiri...
and Tuk.
(GASPS)
Son, you listen to me
very carefully.
You pull back right now.
Do not make a sound.
You get the hell out of there.
Move! You copy?
Yes, sir, moving out.
- See, I told you!
- LO'AK: Go, go.
Dad,
I know a quick way!
(YELPS)
You're going to be
in so much trouble.
Shh! Kiri, stop.
Guys, come on.
It's almost eclipse, come on.
- (TUK SHRIEKS)
- KIRI: Tuk!
(SNARLS)
Put it down!
Down!
Put it down or I'll shoot you!
With me.
- RECOM: Drop it! Right now!
- (SNARLS)
Do not move!
Put your hands up!
(IN NA'VI)
- FIKE: (IN ENGLISH) Hands up!
- KIRI: Spider.
- Down!
- FIKE: Get 'em! Get 'em!
- TUK: Kiri!
- Get over here! Come on!
- (GROANING)
- Get down!
- (GRUNTS)
- Stop fighting.
- (SNARLING)
- RECOM: Don't move!
FIKE: Check 'em
for weapons!
- (WHIMPERS) Kiri!
- KIRI: Tuk.
(IN NA'VI)
(KIRI SPEAKS NA'VI)
(IN ENGLISH)
Shut up. Don't move.
What have we here?
(KIRI PANTING)
- Stop.
- (TUK GRUNTS)
- (SPEAKS NA'VI)
- Hey, Colonel,
check it out.
Four fingers.
We got a half-breed.
(QUIETLY) Shit...
(GRUNTS)
(KIRI BREATHES HEAVILY)
Show me your fingers.
(CHUCKLES)
You're his, aren't you?
(SNARLS)
You're his, all right.
- (LO'AK GROANS)
- SPIDER: Lo'ak, don't.
Don't!
(GROWLS)
Where is he?
(IN NA'VI)
(SNARLING)
(IN ENGLISH) No!
- (SNARLS)
- QUARITCH: Really?
You wanna play it this way?
(KIRI SHOUTS IN NA'VI)
- FIKE: Shut up!
- (KIRI SHOUTS IN NA'VI)
Kiri!
No!
Stop!
Hey! Hey, don't touch her!
(GRUNTS)
Hey!
Don't hurt her, please.
(HISSES)
RECOM: Don't move.
What's your name, kid?
(PANTING)
Spider...
Socorro.
Miles?
Nobody calls me that.
Well, I'll be damned...
Well, I figured they sent you
back to Earth.
They can't put babies
in cryo, dipshit.
What are we doin', boss?
Iron Sky, Blue One, Actual.
Blue One, Iron Sky,
send your traffic.
QUARITCH: We are standing by
for extract, over.
Take us in.
Dragonfly comin' left,
we are go for extract.
Be advised,
we are bringin' in
high value prisoners.
- Let us go!
- Shut up.
Sit tight, Blue One,
we're inbound to your pos.
That's bingo in ten.
We're on the clock.
- ZDINARSIK: Sit!
- FIKE: Come on, in the dirt!
- ZDINARSIK: Feet up!
- Get down on the ground!
Lyle, get me some audio on this.
- ZDINARSIK: Shut your mouth.
- RECOM: Don't look up!
- (SNARLS)
- That's Sully's woman.
(KIRI GRUNTS)
WAINFLEET: She's an animal.
JAKE: Give it up, Quaritch.
Sully.
- It's all over.
- Son of a bitch.
QUARITCH: Nothin's over
while I'm breathin'.
I kinda hoped you'd say that.
(JAKE GRUNTS, YELLS)
(JAKE GRUNTING)
(IKRAN NICKERS)
(SOFTLY) Down, down, down.
No, no, you stay with the ikran.
But, Dad...
I'm a warrior like you.
I'm supposed to fight.
Neteyam.
I'm not gonna say it again.
(SNIFFLES) Yes, sir.
(JAKE EXHALES)
(NEYTIRI GRUNTS)
(QUARITCH GROANS)
(BREATH SHUDDERS)
(THUD)
Yeah, there's nothin'
after that.
You want us to recover
these remains?
(WISTFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
GENERAL ARDMORE:
Blue One, stand by ready.
We are three minutes out.
- QUARITCH: Heads up, three minutes.
- (INSECT BUZZING)
(SNIFFING)
(GASPS)
Watch our six.
(KIRI GRUNTING)
- (DISTANT YIPPING)
- (GASPS)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(DISTANT YIPPING)
(YIPS)
(DISTANT YIP)
(BREATHING DEEPLY)
(CHANTS IN NA'VI)
- Shut up!
- (GROANS)
(CHANTS IN NA'VI)
(GASPS)
(KIRI CONTINUES
CHANTING IN NA'VI)
(CONTINUES CHANTING IN NA'VI)
Shut up!
Contact rear!
- Contact rear!
- Kiri!
Lo'ak!
- (GAS HISSING)
- Shit. (GROANS)
- (GROWLS)
- (SCREAMS IN PAIN)
- (GROANS) You little shit.
- Lo'ak!
- Tuk, come on. Go, go, go!
- ZDINARSIK: Get back here!
Run!
Grab 'em!
(KIRI GROANS)
(YELLS)
(YELPS)
- Come on!
- (GRUNTING)
Cover! Go!
(GRUNTS)
Come on!
That you,
Mrs. Sully?
I recognize your calling card.
(EXHALES)
Why don't you come on out,
Mrs. Sully?
You and I, we got some
unfinished business.
KIRI: Spider, come!
Demon!
I will kill you as many times
as I have to!
QUARITCH: I guess you and
the Corporal have been pretty
busy, haven't you?
Dropped yourself
a whole litter of
half-breeds.
(GRUNTS)
Na'vi!
JAKE: Move! Go, go, go!
You okay?
You okay, boy?
Yeah.
Okay. With me.
Ready? Ready?
Yes, sir!
Move!
Come on!
(GRUNTS)
(SCREAMS)
Go, go, go!
Flank out. Get after 'em!
- (SCREAMS)
- KIRI: Spider?
Spider!
- Kiri!
- Spider.
Come! Come on.
Spider.
He's down there.
No. (WHIMPERS)
Ma'am, we're at bingo.
Ten minutes in enemy airspace.
Blue One. Get back
to the rally point now.
(GASPING WEAKLY)
Blue One, fall back.
Fall back!
Fall back, fall back!
Move out! Move!
Move, move, move!
- Kiri!
- Spider!
Come, come.
- No.
- Come!
Go, go, go.
Come on. Let's go.
Hey. Hey, it's okay.
You hurt?
- Are you hurt?
- No, I'm okay.
- Tuk, you hurt?
- Daddy!
Hey, hey, it's okay.
(AIRCRAFT HOVERING)
JAKE: Okay,
we're clear.
We're clear.
Everyone okay?
- Mom!
- Tuk. (CRYING)
That's it.
It's okay.
It's okay. We're okay.
Oh, thank you, Great Mother.
Thank you.
Where's Spider?
They took him.
Okay. It's all right,
baby girl.
All right?
He's a tough kid.
All right. Shh.
(SOBBING)
He's gonna be okay.
We're all gonna be okay.
(GROWLING)
(HISSES)
Goddamn!
Come on!
(SNARLS)
Let me out of here!
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
(SNARLING)
He's completely feral.
Thinks he's one of them.
(SPIDER SHOUTS IN NA'VI)
(SPIDER SNARLS, HISSES)
JAKE: This thing.
This Quaritch.
Whatever he is...
- NETEYAM: What's going on?
- (SHUSHES QUIETLY)
JAKE: He can walk
right in here.
He can walk right
under Eywa's nose.
NEYTIRI: This is our family.
This is our home.
JAKE: This is
about our family.
This is about our little ones.
NEYTIRI: I cannot.
You cannot ask this.
I cannot leave my People.
I will not.
He's hunting us.
He's targeting our family.
You cannot ask this!
The children.
Everything they've ever known.
The forest.
This is our home!
He had our children.
He had 'em under his knife!
(SIGHS)
My father gave me
this bow as he lay dying.
(VOICE CRACKING) And he said
protect the People.
You're Toruk Makto!
JAKE: This will protect
the People!
Quaritch has Spider.
And that kid knows everything.
He knows our whole operation,
and he can lead them
right in here.
If the People harbor us,
they will die.
Do you understand?
Look, I got nothing.
I got no plan...
But I can protect this family.
That I can do.
(SIGHS)
(SOLEMN MUSIC PLAYING)
I know one thing.
(CRIES)
Wherever we go,
this family is our fortress.
(BREATHES SHAKILY)
(SIGHS HEAVILY)
(MACHINE WHIRRING)
GENERAL ARDMORE:
Where is Jake Sully?
I don't know! (GROANING)
We know that you know.
SPIDER: I don't know!
Just form a picture
in your mind.
Is it one of
the floating mountains?
SPIDER: Let me
out of here!
He's fighting us.
Give us a minute.
SPIDER: I don't know!
Just form a thought,
and we will see it.
SPIDER: I don't know!
GENERAL ARDMORE:
Look, I don't like this
any more than you do.
(SPIDER YELLS IN PAIN)
Which clans would be
- harboring him?
- I don't know!
You're gonna have to kill me!
- (SPIDER SCREAMS)
- Watch this.
You're peaking
all over the prefrontal.
It's not gonna stop
until you give us something.
- Where is he?
- (SCREAMING)
I don't know, you buttholes!
(VOICE CRACKS) Okay?
I don't know!
(YELLING IN PAIN)
(SPIDER PANTING)
General, let me try
the personal angle.
He's not your son.
(SHUDDERING)
(BREATHING HEAVILY
THROUGH MASK)
(DOOR CLOSES)
(QUARITCH GRUNTS)
Whoa. Whoa, whoa.
Easy, tiger. Easy.
(GRUNTS, SNARLS)
We good?
(SIGHS)
Kid, you got heart.
Those science pukes
leaned on you pretty hard.
But you gave them nothin'.
(EXHALES)
I respect that.
(METAL CLINKS)
I thought you might want this.
That's Colonel Miles Quaritch.
Deceased.
Killed in action.
(LOCKET CLATTERS)
I'm not that man.
But I do have his memories...
enough to know that, uh,
well, he wasn't
always the best father.
But that's not an apology.
I'm not your father.
Technically,
you and I,
we're nothin' to each other.
But...
I can help you.
I can get you outta here.
Ah, I'm not gonna ask you
to betray Jake Sully.
I know you'd never do that.
You're loyal,
and I admire loyalty.
Just ride along.
Otherwise, I gotta give you
back to the lab coats.
(WISTFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
JAKE: This is like stones
in my heart.
Tarsem is wise for his years.
He will be a strong Olo'eyktan.
The leader must die.
(YELLS)
(TARSEM GRUNTS)
So the leader can be born.
Toruk Makto will disappear.
(PEOPLE SOBBING)
The People will be safe.
(SIGHS HEAVILY)
(WISTFUL MUSIC CONTINUES)
(YIPS)
(YELPS)
JAKE: A father protects.
It's what gives him meaning.
One life ends.
Another begins.
- (MUSIC SWELLING)
- (THUNDER RUMBLING)
(IKRAN SCREECHES)
(SIGHS) Tuk.
JAKE: The sea clans are
a world unto themselves.
(IKRAN TRILLS)
Thousands of islands.
An unknown territory
into which we could
just vanish without a trace.
Are we there yet?
(CAPTIVATING MUSIC PLAYING)
(PEOPLE YIPPING)
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
(BLISSFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(BLOWS LONG NOTE)
(PEOPLE YIPPING AND HOOTING)
(IKRAN TRILLS)
(CONTINUES BLOWING CONCH)
(JAKE WHOOPING)
(YIPPING)
(SQUAWKING)
(EXHALES)
Hey,
leave it.
On me.
Tuk.
(PEOPLE YIPPING)
- JAKE: Be nice.
- TUK: Who...
- Who are they?
- NEYTIRI: Be nice.
Hey.
(PEOPLE WHISPERING)
WOMAN: We don't know
why they are here.
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYS)
MAN: Where did
they come from?
JAKE: Easy.
Just be cool.
Look.
What is that?
Is that supposed to be a tail?
(LAUGHTER)
(SERENE MUSIC PLAYING)
- It's too small.
- (BOYS CHUCKLE)
How are they supposed to swim?
Do not.
Rotxo, Aonung.
(SIGHS)
Hey.
(CHUCKLES SHYLY)
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
- (SHOUTS)
- (SKIMWING SNARLS)
(GRUNTS)
JAKE: Tonowari was the chief
of the Metkayina,
the Reef People.
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
JAKE: I See you,
Tonowari.
Jakesully.
JAKE: I knew him
as a tough leader.
(EXCHANGING GREETINGS
IN NA'VI)
But it wasn't Tonowari
I was worried about.
I See you, Ronal.
Tsahik of the Metkayina.
NEYTIRI: I See you, Ronal.
Why do you come to us,
Jakesully?
We seek uturu.
Uturu?
Yes, sanctuary for my family.
We are Reef People.
You are Forest People.
Your skills
will mean nothing here.
Well, we will learn your ways.
Am I right?
NEYTIRI: Yes.
Their arms are thin.
- Mom.
- Their tails...
- Ow.
- ...are weak.
You will be slow in the water.
These children
- are not even true Na'vi.
- Dad.
(CROWD GASPS)
Yes, we are!
They have demon blood!
(CROWD GASPS AND EXCLAIMS)
Look. Look.
Look, I was born
of the Sky People,
and now I am Na'vi.
All right? You can adapt.
We will adapt.
Okay?
My husband was Toruk Makto.
He led the clans to victory
against the Sky People.
This you call victory?
Hiding among strangers?
It seems Eywa has turned
her back on you,
Chosen One.
(BOTH SNARLING AND HISSING)
I apologize for my mate.
She's...
Do not apologize for me.
...flown a long way,
and she's exhausted.
Jake.
(RONAL AND NEYTIRI
BREATHE HEAVILY)
Toruk Makto
is a great war leader.
All Na'vi people know his story.
But we Metkayina...
- TUK: Dad.
- ...are not at war.
We cannot let you
bring your war here.
I'm done with war.
Okay?
I just want to keep
my family safe.
Uturu has been asked.
(TONOWARI SIGHS)
TUK: Do we have to go?
Shh, we'll be okay.
(TONOWARI INHALES SHARPLY)
Toruk Makto and his family
will stay with us.
Treat them
as our brothers and sisters.
Now, they do not know the sea.
So they will be like babies
taking their first breath.
Teach them our ways,
so they do not suffer
the shame of being
useless.
(JAKE CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
Okay, what do we say?
Thank you.
- JAKE: Thank you.
- NETEYAM: Thank you.
(QUIETLY) Thank you.
My son, Aonung,
our daughter, Tsireya,
will show your children
what to do.
- Father, why do...
- It is decided.
Come. I will show you
our village.
(ANIMALS TRILLING)
(TUK GIGGLING)
TSIREYA: This way.
- (TUK GASPS)
- (ANIMAL SQUEAKS)
- (GIGGLING)
- KIRI: Tuk, let's go.
TSIREYA: Just up here.
No, no.
(TUK GRUNTING EXCITEDLY)
(ANIMAL SQUEAKS)
This is for you.
- Your new home.
- (JAKE PANTING)
Yeah, this will work.
This is great.
It's nice, right?
(NEYTIRI SIGHS)
- (CALM MUSIC PLAYING)
- (BIRDS CALLING)
JAKE: Okay, Sullys, fall in.
Remember? Family meeting.
JAKE: Come on.
Take a knee. Let's go.
Kiri.
What?
JAKE: Okay. (EXHALES)
I need you kids
on your best behavior.
I mean it.
Learn fast.
Pull your weight.
Don't cause trouble.
You got it?
- Yes, sir.
- (NETEYAM CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
(SNARLS)
I want to go home.
(CRYING)
Oh, Tuk.
Tuk, this is our home now.
Now we're gonna
get through this.
We're gonna get through this
if we have each other's backs.
All right?
What does your father
always say?
BOTH: Sullys stick together.
JAKE: That's right.
Sullys stick together.
Now this time with some feeling.
Yeah.
Sullys stick together.
(RELUCTANTLY)
(SERENE MUSIC PLAYING)
NETEYAM: Come on.
LO'AK: Whoo-hoo!
(INHALES SHARPLY)
- (TUK SCREAMS)
- KIRI: Whoo!
(SERENE MUSIC CONTINUES)
(BOTH GASPING)
(SIGNING)
(BOTH INHALE DEEPLY)
Are you all right?
You're too fast!
Wait for us.
Just breathe.
Breathe.
You are not good divers.
Maybe good at swinging
through trees, but...
(ROTXO LAUGHS)
Come on, bro.
We don't speak
this finger talk, guys.
We don't know
what you're saying.
I will teach you.
- ROTXO: Where is Kiri?
- TUK: Kiri?
- AONUNG: Who?
- ROTXO: Kiri.
Where is Kiri?
TSIREYA: Did you see her?
(DREAMY MUSIC PLAYING)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
Get on the ship,
find a seat,
and keep out of the way.
RECOM: Ready for transport!
Let's go!
Chop-chop.
SPIDER: Sweet.
QUARITCH: Whoa,
hold on there, hotshot!
You listen up.
There's a tracker
built in that mask.
We hit the ground,
and you take off,
I'll have you back
in two minutes,
and I will give you
a old-school ass-whippin'.
Understood?
Yes, sir.
We up?
Team's up.
QUARITCH:
All right, listen up.
Jake Sully's gone to ground.
Don't matter.
Wherever he is, we'll find him,
and his batshit crazy wife, too.
(SQUAD CHUCKLES)
To do so,
we go Na'vi.
Full tilt, all the way.
That means we eat Na'vi.
We ride Na'vi.
Think Na'vi.
(IN NA'VI)
(CHUCKLES)
(IN ENGLISH)
All right, smart guy.
You just went from
bein' our monkey mascot
- to official interpreter.
- (WAINFLEET CHUCKLES)
(WHOOPING AND CLICKING TONGUE)
- (ANIMAL GRUNTS)
- (TSIREYA YIPS)
- These are ilu.
If you want to live here,
you have to ride.
Make the bond gently.
(SOFT CRACKLE)
(ILU MOANS)
Feel his breath.
Feel his strength.
(BREATHES DEEPLY)
Hold here.
Look at his legs.
- AONUNG: Hold on.
- (INHALES SHARPLY)
(MUFFLED GRUNTING)
(LAUGHS)
(ALL LAUGH)
(GASPS)
(SQUAWKS)
(BOYS LAUGHING)
- (GIGGLES)
- BOY: You all right,
Forest Boy?
(SKIMWING GROWLS AND HISSES)
(SKIMWING GRUNTS)
(SNARLING)
This is a warrior's mount.
Not easy to master.
Perhaps you should
start with an ilu.
JAKE: Nah.
This one.
TONOWARI: Now remember,
when you dive back in,
good position.
Very important.
- JAKE: Uh-huh. (GRUNTS)
- (SKIMWING GROWLS SOFTLY)
I got this.
- Whew!
- (SKIMWING CLICKS)
Hyah!
Come on.
(SCREECHES)
(JAKE GRUNTING)
(WARRIOR LAUGHS)
(GRUNTING)
(SKIMWING SCREECHING)
That's it, okay.
(SCREECHES)
Steady.
(INHALES DEEPLY)
(JAKE GRUNTS)
- (WARRIORS LAUGH)
- (TONOWARI SIGHS)
(GRUNTING IN FRUSTRATION)
- Ah, shit.
- (SKIMWING SCREECHES)
(ILU BELLOWING SOFTLY)
(ILU SQUEAKS)
(ILU CLICKS, SQUEAKS)
(ILU GRUNTS)
(GIGGLING)
(SQUEAKING)
I love her already.
(ILU CLICKS)
(SQUEAKS)
(ENCHANTING MUSIC PLAYING)
(ILU CLICKS)
(ILU CHIRPS)
(ILU CLICKING)
(ILU CHIRPING)
(ILU SQUEAKING AND CLICKING)
Breathe in. (INHALES DEEPLY)
(ALL INHALE DEEPLY)
- And breathe out.
- (ALL EXHALE DEEPLY)
Imagine flickering a flame.
You must slow down
your heartbeat.
- Breathe in.
- (INHALES DEEPLY)
Breathe from down here.
- Breathe out slowly.
- (EXHALES SLOWLY)
Lo'ak, your heartbeat is fast.
- Sorry.
- Try to focus.
- Okay.
- Breathe in.
- (BOTH SNICKERING)
- And breathe out.
- Let your mind go clear.
- (SIGHS)
(ILU SQUEAKING)
(ENCHANTING MUSIC PLAYING)
- (PANTING)
- NETEYAM: Whoo!
- (CHUCKLES)
- You are learning to breathe.
(IKRAN SCREECHING)
SPIDER: Come on!
Keep up, losers!
(IKRAN ROARING)
I got this.
(LAUGHS)
What?
Na'vi kids younger than me
do this with their bare hands.
Jake Sully did it the hard way?
What do you think?
What are we doin', Colonel?
(ROARING)
(CHUCKLES)
This is gonna be good.
(INHALES SHARPLY)
WAINFLEET: All right, move up.
(IKRAN SCREECHING, HISSING)
(IKRAN SCREECHES)
QUARITCH:
It's you and me, cupcake.
(HISSES)
(GRUNTING)
- (GRUNTS)
- Ooh.
Did I mention you're supposed
to tie the mouth shut first?
Thanks a lot, kid!
(SCREECHING)
Whoa... Whoa!
WAINFLEET:
Move up, move up!
(SCREAMING)
You see 'em?
(ROUSING MUSIC PLAYING)
(INHALES DEEPLY)
Whew! (CHUCKLES)
WAINFLEET: All right,
let's go. We're Oscar Mike.
Come on.
Let's go.
We're outta here.
(SIGHS)
(WHOOPING) Yeah!
That's right!
(SQUAD CHEERING)
Yeah, Colonel!
Get some!
RECOM: Yeah, Colonel!
Who's up next?
(SQUAD CHEERING)
(WAINFLEET LAUGHS)
(BOTH BREATHING DEEPLY)
The way of water has
no beginning and no end.
(SOFT MUSIC PLAYING)
The sea is around you
and in you.
(BREATHING SHARPLY)
The sea is your home
before your birth
and after your death.
Our hearts beat
in the womb of the world.
Our breath burns
in the shadows of the deep.
The sea gives
and the sea takes.
Water connects all things.
Life to death.
Darkness
to light.
(GASPING)
- I got it!
- (CHUCKLES)
- Tsireya!
- You did it! (CHUCKLES)
(DREAMY MUSIC PLAYING)
(SQUELCHING)
(SIGNING)
(DREAMY MUSIC CONTINUES)
- AONUNG: What is she doing?
- (BOYS LAUGH)
ROTXO: I don't know.
AONUNG: She's just
looking at the sand.
(BOYS LAUGH)
Huh?
What'd you say?
Are you some kind of...
freak?
He asked if you are a freak.
(SIGHS)
No.
- (LAUGHTER)
- Are you sure?
I mean, you're
not even real Na'vi.
Look at these hands.
I mean, look at them...
- (BOYS LAUGH)
- LO'AK: Hey!
Back off, fishlips!
Oh, another four-fingered freak.
Look at his little baby tail!
- Don't touch me!
- Aw, baby tail!
Leave us alone!
He's not normal.
- BOY 2: Look at his tail.
- AONUNG: Aw, baby tail!
It is so cute!
You heard what she said.
Leave them alone.
Ah, big brother come...
Back off.
Now.
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(SCOFFS SOFTLY)
Smart choice.
And from now on,
I need you to respect my sister.
(HISSES)
NETEYAM: Let's go.
Buh-bye!
- Look at them.
- (BOYS CHUCKLING)
They're all freaks.
- The whole family.
- (LO'AK SIGHS DEEPLY)
Lo'ak.
I got this, bro.
I know this hand is funny.
Look, I'm a freak.
An alien.
(BOYS CHUCKLE)
But it can do
something really cool.
Watch.
First, I ball it up
real tight like this.
Okay? Then...
(BOTH GRUNTING)
It's called a punch, bitch!
Don't ever touch
my sister again.
(BOYS HISS AND SNARL)
BOY: Yeah! Aonung!
Show him!
- ROTXO: Come here!
- (BOYS GRUNT)
NETEYAM: Hey! Hey!
(BOYS LAUGH)
(NETEYAM SIGHS)
- KIRI: Stop this!
- (GRUNTS)
Stop it!
(ALL GRUNTING)
So stupid!
LO'AK: Ow, my tail!
My ear!
Let go!
- He's got my ear!
- (LAUGHING)
(MAN SHOUTS IN DISTANCE)
What was the one thing
I asked? The one thing!
- Stay out of trouble.
- Right.
- It was my fault.
I don't think so.
You gotta stop takin' the heat
for this knucklehead.
Look, Dad.
Aonung was picking on Kiri.
He called her a freak.
(SIGHS)
Go apologize to Aonung.
What?
He is the chief's son.
Do you understand?
I don't care how you do it.
Just go make peace.
Just go.
Hey.
So what'd
the other guys look like?
Worse.
That's good.
A lot worse.
Get outta here.
(SIGHS)
What is wrong?
Nothing. I'm fine.
Why should I not be fine?
(KIRI BREATHING HEAVILY)
Why can't I just be
like everyone else?
(SOFTLY) Oh, Kiri.
(ILU SQUEAKING)
Ah, what's tree boy doing here?
I'm sorry I hit you.
So many times.
Ah.
We should be friends.
Come hunting with us.
Outside the reef.
It's where the men hunt.
- No way. I'm not allowed.
- (SCOFFS)
I must be asking
the wrong brother.
Let's do it.
Ah!
- (YIPS)
- (ILU SQUEAKS)
(THRILLING MUSIC PLAYING)
(BOYS WHOOPING)
AONUNG: Come on! Come on!
Yeah!
(CHUCKLES) Whoo!
Keep up, Forest Boy!
LO'AK: Whoo-hoo! Yeah!
(BIRDS CALLING)
(ILU MOANS)
(GASPING)
- Hey, you lived!
- Whoo!
That was insane, cuz!
(BOY LAUGHS)
This way.
I know a good spot.
- (ILU SQUEAKS)
- (BOYS YIP)
(SERENE MUSIC PLAYING)
(SIGNING)
(AONUNG GRUNTS)
(GRUNTING INTERMITTENTLY)
(CONTINUES GRUNTING
INTERMITTENTLY)
Hey, guys!
Hey!
Aonung!
Come on, this isn't funny!
(OMINOUS MUSIC PLAYS)
Hey, Aonung!
- (SCREAMS)
- (ILU YELPS)
(ILU SCREECHES)
(ILU YELPING)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(TENSE MUSIC CONTINUES)
(HEART BEATING RAPIDLY)
(GAGGING)
(GRUNTS)
(HEARTBEAT SLOWS)
(GRUNTING)
(OMINOUS MUSIC PLAYS)
(GRUNTS)
(GROANING)
(GAGGING)
(CONTINUES GAGGING)
(GAGS)
(SOFT MUSIC PLAYING)
(MUSIC FADES)
(WAVES CRASHING)
(BREATHING SOFTLY)
(INHALES SHARPLY)
(BIRDS CALLING IN DISTANCE)
(PANTING)
(BLOWING)
Holy shit.
(GENTLE MUSIC PLAYING)
(ANIMAL GROANS, CLICKS)
You're a tulkun.
(TULKUN MOANING)
You saved my life.
Thank you.
(TULKUN RUMBLING
AND SQUEAKING)
(CHUCKLES)
Buddy, I have no idea
what you just said.
(TULKUN MOANS, RUMBLES)
They hurt you, didn't they?
(TULKUN MOANS)
(MUFFLED)
I'll try to pull it out.
Just trust me, okay?
(GRUNTS)
(INHALES DEEPLY)
(TULKUN CLICKS)
(GRUNTS)
(METAL SQUEAKING)
(LO'AK PANTING)
(TULKUN WHISTLES, SINGS)
Friends?
(TULKUN BELLOWS, SQUEAKS)
(CHUCKLES)
That's right, we're friends.
- Friends.
- (CLICKS)
- (GRUNTS)
- Oh!
Whoa, whoa! Bro!
(GENTLE MUSIC PLAYING)
(TULKUN WHISTLES)
(TULKUN CLICKS)
(TULKUN SNORTS, WHISTLES)
(ROUSING MUSIC PLAYING)
(TULKUN CLICKS)
(TULKUN WHISTLES)
(TULKUN CLICKS, MOANS)
(TULKUN MOANS)
(SIGNING)
(GENTLE MUSIC PLAYING)
(SOFT MUSIC PLAYING)
(JAKE EXHALES)
So, what is it, baby girl?
- You missin' Spider?
- (EXHALES)
(KIRI SNIFFLES)
- Yeah.
- Yeah?
But that's not it.
Okay...
- So what is it?
- (BREATHING HEAVILY)
I feel her, Dad.
You feel who?
Eywa.
I hear her breathing.
I hear her heartbeat.
She's so close.
She's just there...
like a word about to be spoken.
(INHALES)
I know you think I'm crazy.
You're not crazy, baby girl.
So what does Eywa's
heartbeat sound like?
Mighty.
Tell him what you told me!
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
LO'AK: You like
lookin' at the stars?
(TULKUN GRUNTS, WHISTLES)
You know, my dad
came from a star.
That one.
Right there.
JAKE: (YIPS) Lo'ak!
Oh, man.
I'm in trouble.
(TULKUN MOANS)
(DISTANT HOOTING)
Go. I will see you again.
(TULKUN WHISTLES)
(DISTANT YIPPING)
(CONCH BLOWS)
(YIPPING)
- WOMAN: The boy has returned!
- MAN 1: It is the Sully boy.
- MAN 2: They found the boy.
- MAN 1: They found him.
MAN 2: They found the boy.
(BREATHES HEAVILY)
Hey, hey.
(LO'AK BREATHES SHAKILY)
Let's have a look
at you. Okay.
He's fine.
He's fine,
- yeah. Just a few scratches.
- NEYTIRI: Lo'ak!
(GASPING)
I pray for the strength
that I will not
pluck the eyeballs out of
my youngest son! (SNARLS)
TONOWARI: No.
My son knows better than
to take him outside the reef.
The blame is his.
Okay, let's go.
No.
This is not Aonung's fault.
This was my idea.
Aonung tried
to talk me out of it.
Really.
JAKE: Come on.
NEYTIRI: Lo'ak.
LO'AK: I'm sorry.
JAKE: Come on.
(WHISPERS) I got this.
Is this true?
Aonung.
What were you thinking?
Dad, you told me to make
friends with these kids.
- That's all I was trying to...
- I don't want to hear it.
Dad...
You brought shame
to this family.
(JAKE SIGHS)
Can I go now?
Any more trouble,
I jerk a knot in your tail.
You read me?
Yes, sir.
Lima Charlie.
(SOFTLY) Go on.
(SIGHS)
Where were you?
Yeah.
What happened to
"keep an eye on your brother"?
Sorry, sir.
Why did you speak for me?
Because I know what it's like
to be one big disappointment.
(SCOFFS)
I wish I'd been there.
The ocean blessed you
with a gift, brother.
The tulkun
have not returned yet.
And anyway,
no tulkun is ever alone.
Well, this one was.
He had a missing fin.
Like a stump.
- On the left side.
- Poor tulkun.
Payakan.
- What?
- It's Payakan.
Who's Payakan?
A young bull who went rogue.
He's outcast.
Alone.
And he has a missing fin.
They say he is a killer.
- No, no.
- He killed Na'vi,
and other tulkun.
Not here, but far to the south.
- No, he's no killer.
- TSIREYA: Lo'ak,
you are lucky to be alive.
I'm telling you guys.
He saved my life.
He's my friend.
My baby bro!
The Mighty Warrior
who faced the killer tulkun,
and lived to tell about it, huh?
(LO'AK GRUNTS)
You guys aren't listening.
- (SIGHS)
- TUK: Lo'ak, I'm listening.
KIRI: Lo'ak, come back.
You skxawngs.
- Payakan!
- (WHINES)
Payakan!
(ILU SQUEAKS)
- Payakan!
- (WATER RUMBLES)
(PAYAKAN RUMBLES)
- It's good to see you.
- (PAYAKAN GRUNTS)
Why are you outcast?
What happened?
(PAYAKAN WHINES AND CLICKS)
(MUFFLED) I trust you.
You can trust me.
(PAYAKAN GRUNTS SOFTLY)
(CAPTIVATING MUSIC PLAYING)
- (PAYAKAN MOANS)
- (CHUCKLES)
(ULULATING)
(GRUNTS)
Bro, that's disgusting!
(GRUNTS SOFTLY)
(SIGNING)
(PAYAKAN MOANS)
(STIRRING MUSIC PLAYING)
Whoo-hoo!
(SERENE MUSIC PLAYING)
We are here.
(MUSIC FLOURISHES)
This is the Cove
of the Ancestors.
Our most sacred place.
(KIRI SIGHS IN AWE)
Eclipse is the best
time of day to be here.
(SERENE MUSIC CONTINUES)
This is it.
This is the Spirit Tree.
(ENCHANTING MUSIC PLAYING)
(SOFT CRACKLE)
(WHOOSHING)
(SOFT MUSIC PLAYING)
(ECHOING) My beautiful daughter.
Hi, Ma.
I'm so happy to see you.
But you look troubled.
- (SNIFFLING)
- (GRACE EXHALES)
Oh. (SHUSHING SOFTLY)
My sweet girl.
It will be okay.
(GRACE SHUSHING SOFTLY)
(CRYING SOFTLY)
What is it, baby?
Why am I different?
What does the Great Mother
want from me?
Who was my father?
Oh...
Oh, my darling.
- (STIFLED GRUNTING)
- (OMINOUS MUSIC PLAYS)
(SCREAMS)
No!
(GRUNTING)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(GAGGING)
- Come on.
- TUK: Kiri!
(ILU SQUAWKS)
Kiri!
What is wrong?
What is it?
NETEYAM: It was a seizure.
- Is she breathing?
- (BLOWING)
Is she breathing?
(COUGHING AND GASPING)
Get her to the village!
Hurry!
Let's go!
Let's move!
TSIREYA: Tuk, come. (YIPS)
(JAKE GRUNTS)
- Hi!
- It's good to see you.
Let's get the gear.
Neteyam!
Neteyam, keep them back!
How is she?
She's still unconscious.
- (MACHINE BEEPING)
- MAX: There's no bleed.
There's no fracture.
No effects of hypoxia.
The brain looks good.
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
But we still have
this interictal activity
right here in the prefrontal.
Okay.
MAX: She's definitely
had a seizure.
I think we can rule out toxins.
JAKE: So what is it?
MAX: Until this point...
I see that I am not needed here.
You are Tsahik!
Remove these things.
Out! You have done nothing!
Come on, come on.
Let's just take a break.
In the middle...
Okay, hold on.
I gotta take her IV off.
Tuktirey.
(CHANTING IN NA'VI)
She said that she can feel Eywa.
She can hear her heartbeat.
- That's it.
- What?
That is classic
frontal lobe epilepsy.
- Epilepsy?
- Yep.
You see visions.
You get
states of religious ecstasy
like the kind she's describing.
(BLOWING RAPIDLY)
(BLOWS SHARPLY)
Pluggin' into the Spirit Tree
is some sort of a trigger.
You definitely can't let her
do that anymore.
What? Ever?
Jake.
If she seizes underwater again,
it could kill her.
(BLOWING)
(INHALES DEEPLY)
(BLOWS SHARPLY)
(RONAL BLOWING)
- TUK: Kiri!
- (GRUNTS SOFTLY)
(GASPS) You're awake!
(RONAL SIGHS HEAVILY)
(CRYING)
- (CRYING)
- NEYTIRI: Oh, Kiri.
Kiri, my sweet child.
Oh, my sweet little girl.
Okay, this one.
"I See you."
Oel ngati kameie.
Ngaati. (CHUCKLES) Ngaati!
That's what I just said,
isn't it?
Oel ngati kameie.
Not "Naati. Ngaati."
Ngaati, ngaati.
All right. Like comin' out
your nose or something.
- (SPIDER CHUCKLES)
- Boss,
long-range patrol
picked up a radar hit.
A rogue gunship.
Where?
WAINFLEET: Eastern sea.
Four hundred klicks north.
Uh-huh.
- Hang on.
- (SQUAWKS)
QUARITCH:
The signal was intermittent,
and they lost it
over open water but...
if you project the track,
it hits this island group.
That's hundreds of islands.
That's a big search box
with lots of villages.
This is our guy.
You give me ships and aircraft,
I'll bring you back his scalp.
(OMINOUS MUSIC PLAYING)
Bogies inbound.
Skipper.
(IKRAN SQUAWKING)
- All stop.
All stop. Aye.
(ENGINE SLOWS DOWN)
(IKRAN SQUAWKING)
Hey.
You Scoresby?
Uh-huh.
Are you the asshole
who's commandeering my ship?
- That would be me.
- (SQUAWKS)
The target's pretty much
this whole island group.
Never been up there.
You know those waters, doc.
What kinda indigenous we got?
Uh, Metkayina, mostly.
Some Ta'unui.
Maybe fifty villages.
And you are who?
Oh. Uh, I'm Ian Garvin.
Marine biologist.
Fifty villages.
A hundred villages.
I don't care.
We'll search 'em all.
I hunt tulkun.
That's what I'm rigged for.
That's all my guys do.
I've got quotas to meet.
I'll be nice once.
- Then I won't.
- (WAINFLEET INHALES)
Well, if you can't
get out of it,
get into it!
- All crews to stations!
- CREWMAN: Hey, don't touch.
Helm, bring her up.
Flight speed.
Flight speed, aye.
- (CONCH BLOWS)
- (TUK GASPS)
- (EXCITED CHATTERING)
- What was that?
- GIRL: They're coming!
- LO'AK: What's going on?
(CONCH CONTINUES BLOWING)
The tulkun have returned!
Everybody, our Brothers
and Sisters have returned.
(CAPTIVATING MUSIC PLAYING)
JAKE: In their endless cycle
of migration,
the tulkun had come home.
- (SHOUTING)
- (TULKUN CALLING)
- (MAN 1 WHOOPING)
- MAN 2: I See you!
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
TUK: Kiri!
Kiri, come on. Come on!
Tuk, leave me alone.
- Come on!
- What?
(GROANS) What do you want?
Look. Look.
(CAPTIVATING MUSIC CONTINUES)
(TULKUN CALLING)
- Come on.
- (CHUCKLING)
Let's go meet them.
Look,
it's my Spirit Sister.
(TULKUN CALLS)
(LAUGHS)
(TULKUN SINGING)
(TULKUN GRUNTS, BELLOWS)
(ILU CLICKING)
(ILU CHIRPS)
(TULKUN MOANS)
(YOUNG TULKUN CALLS)
(ILU CHIRPS, CLICKS)
(TULKUN MOANS)
(ILU SQUEAKS)
(ILU CHIRPS)
(TULKUN MOANS, CLICKS)
(SIGNING)
(TULKUN CLICKING)
(YOUNG TULKUN SINGING)
(SIGNING)
(TULKUN TRILLING)
(TULKUN MOANS)
(SIGNING)
JAKE: It was
a time for stories.
Of their season apart.
Of deaths and births.
- (BABY GASPS)
- (TULKUN TRILLS SOFTLY)
Of old friends
and new loves.
(CAPTIVATING MUSIC CONTINUES)
(TULKUN GRUNTS SOFTLY, CLICKS)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
- (WORRIED CHATTER)
- Children.
Be calm,
my people.
TROOPER: We're looking
for weapons, comms.
Any kind of tech.
Get down.
You too.
You see this?
-WAINFLEET: Get down
-(CATTLE PRODS ZAPPING)
- (GROANS)
- Stay down and shut up!
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
(IN NA'VI)
(IN ENGLISH)
Now what's he saying?
They never saw him.
These are Sea People.
Forest People don't come here.
I ain't buyin' that.
(QUARRELLING IN NA'VI)
(IN NA'VI)
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
(IN ENGLISH)
They don't know anything.
Shoot that animal.
(YELPS)
What the hell are you doing?
- (GASPS)
- (YELLS)
(ALL EXCLAIM)
WAINFLEET: Down!
(SHOUTS IN NA'VI)
(IN NA'VI)
(IN ENGLISH)
Hey, your ears workin' now?
(IN NA'VI)
(IN ENGLISH) You see
what these can do, huh?
(TA'UNUI TSAHIK
PLEADS IN NA'VI)
(QUARITCH SPEAKS NA'VI)
Jake Sully.
(SPIDER SPEAKING NA'VI)
Toruk Makto!
(IN NA'VI)
- (IN ENGLISH) Put her down!
- WAINFLEET: Get down!
(ALL EXCLAIM ANGRILY)
- Get down!
- (CATTLE PROD ZAPPING)
Stop!
You make it real clear to him.
He doesn't give up Sully,
we kill the Tsahik.
No, I'm not doin' that.
Is that right?
I'm not gonna be a part of this!
- (ANGRY SHOUTING)
- ZDINARSIK: Get down!
These people
don't know anything!
They don't know anything!
- ZDINARSIK: Don't move!
- TROOPER: Stay down.
- (TA'UNUI TSAHIK SPEAKS NA'VI)
- TROOPER: Shut up!
We really gonna waste her?
SPIDER: Please.
Please don't do this.
This is wrong.
What you're doing here is wrong.
Please.
(TA'UNUI TSAHIK
SPEAKING TEARFULLY IN NA'VI)
Burn the hooches.
Hey, light 'em up.
Light 'em up. All of 'em!
- TROOPER 2: Flamethrowers up!
- TROOPER 3: Light 'em up.
(VILLAGERS SHOUTING)
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
(IN NA'VI)
(IN ENGLISH) I'm sorry.
- We're outta here.
- (SPIDER SPEAKING NA'VI)
(IN ENGLISH)
Don't touch me!
I'm sorry.
- QUARITCH: Let's go.
- (APOLOGIZES IN NA'VI)
- Saddle up.
- All right. Let's go.
(VILLAGERS WAILING)
(SOMBER MUSIC PLAYING)
(JAKE AND NEYTIRI LAUGHING)
What's wrong?
Sky People.
They're looking for you,
Jakesully.
South.
They have a human boy
who speaks Na'vi.
Did they kill anybody?
Not yet.
They threaten.
But the villagers will not
tell them where you are.
By my order.
We must hunt this demon.
Trap him.
Kill him.
- (BREATHING HEAVILY)
- We've gotta be smart.
- (INHALES SHARPLY)
- We gotta be smart.
If we hit Quaritch,
they're gonna know where we are,
and they're gonna come here
with everything they've got.
(BREATHES HEAVILY)
Then what is our plan?
That's Toruk Makto!
- ZDINARSIK: Head down.
- (QUARITCH SPEAKS NA'VI)
Has he been here?
- (VILLAGERS CLAMORING)
- (CATTLE PROD CRACKLING)
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
This shit ain't workin'.
Nah, they're stonewallin' us.
If we turn up the heat,
he's just gonna keep runnin'.
- We gotta draw him out.
- (SIGHS)
(IKRAN SQUAWKS)
SCORESBY: I'm over it.
I've got quotas to meet.
You wanna hunt?
Let's hunt.
- Come on.
- SCORESBY: Here? Not here.
There's too many villages.
No.
No, no, no.
Respectfully, sir, uh,
you do not understand
the kinship bonds
between the tulkun
and the ocean Na'vi.
It would be like murdering
a member of their family.
If we start hunting here,
the hostiles will come after us.
Exactly.
One hostile in particular.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(PAYAKAN GRUNTS)
(MUFFLED) I know how you feel.
I feel all alone too.
Tell me.
(CLEARLY) Why are you outcast?
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYS)
(SOFT PENSIVE MUSIC PLAYING)
(CRACKLING)
(GASPS SOFTLY)
(EXPLOSION)
(TULKUN WAILING)
(WHIMPERS)
(EXPLOSIONS)
(TULKUN CRIES)
(EXPLOSION)
- (TULKUN WAILING)
- (EXPLOSIONS CONTINUE)
(SOMBER MUSIC PLAYING)
(GASPING)
(PAYAKAN RUMBLING LOWLY)
(PANTING) I'm sorry.
I'm so sorry.
(PAYAKAN WHINES)
(SOFTLY) It's okay.
It's okay.
(RONAL BREATHING HEAVILY)
(EXHALES SHARPLY)
You allowed this.
You allowed him to bond
with the outcast!
(TSIREYA BREATHING SHAKILY)
- Tsireya.
- (INHALES SHARPLY)
You disappoint me, daughter.
And you,
son of a great warrior,
who has been taught better.
Payakan saved my life, sir.
You don't know him.
TSIREYA: No, Lo'ak.
Sit.
- Sit down!
- (TSIREYA WHIMPERS)
(BLOWS SHARPLY)
Hear my words, boy.
In the days of the First Songs,
tulkun fought
amongst themselves,
for territory,
and for revenge.
But they came to believe
that killing,
no matter how justified,
only brings more killing.
So all killing was forbidden.
This is the Tulkun Way.
Payakan
is a killer, so,
he is outcast.
I'm sorry, sir.
But you're wrong.
Lo'ak.
You speak to Olo'eyktan!
- I know what I...
- JAKE: That's enough!
- I know what I know.
- (SNARLS)
(LO'AK SIGHS)
That's enough.
I'll deal with this one.
(SIGHS)
This storm will pass.
Lo'ak, I saw something today.
I saw a Forest Boy
chosen by tulkun.
I am very proud of you.
Payakan didn't kill those boys.
I saw it all.
The demon ship killed his mother
right in front of him.
He gathered the young bulls
and the reef boys together
to attack the ship.
And they were all killed,
but by the Sky People.
Not by him.
- He's not a killer.
- No, Lo'ak.
By the Tulkun Way, he is.
He bears those deaths.
Does he have to pay for it
for the rest of his life?
He knows what he did was wrong.
He would never do it again.
(SIGHS)
We must tell my father...
No. No.
I'm in enough trouble
with my dad already.
Your father
will understand this.
No, he won't.
He doesn't understand anything.
The whole clan hates me.
Demon blood.
Alien.
That's all they see.
I See you.
You are Brother of Tulkun.
You are one of us now.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
(AMBIENT MUSIC PLAYING)
(MUSIC BECOMES TENSE)
(BEEPING)
(TULKUN SQUEALS)
SCORESBY: You got my mother?
Mother and calf.
Strong signal. Range 4,000.
Bring it down,
on the hull.
- Comin' down, aye.
- SCORESBY: Whoo!
Foils deployed.
(TENSE MUSIC CONTINUES)
SCORESBY: Sub teams,
two minutes!
Let's get in there!
Hatches closed!
Come on, hustle! Hustle!
Crews to their boats.
Two minutes.
Let's make some bank.
(SNAPS FINGERS)
Boat crews!
Let's get those tie downs off!
Tie downs off!
All boats in! Boats in!
Let's go, baby!
We're rollin'!
(ENGINES ROARING)
SCORESBY: Whoo-hoo-hoo!
Whoo! (LAUGHS)
(SENSOR BEEPING)
(TULKUN SQUEAKING)
Stand by depth charges,
and fire, fire, fire!
(TULKUN SQUEALING)
Ho!
(TULKUN GROANING)
What's that?
What are they doin'?
Those are echolocation sensors.
How they navigate.
They have to hold
them out of the water,
or they'll go deaf.
Picadors!
Get in there! Go on.
Get in there.
Get up in there!
(TENSE MUSIC CONTINUES)
(SOUND CANNON FIRING)
(TULKUN CRIES)
They're gonna cut the cow
from the rest of the pod
using the sound cannon.
They target the mother
because the calf swims slowly,
and she won't leave the calf.
Do they ever fight back?
Nah, never seen 'em lift a fin.
Tough bastards to kill though.
(CHUCKLES)
Sub teams, go!
And release.
Release, release.
GUNNER 1: There's our gal.
- PILOT 1: Target in sight.
- (SENSOR BEEPING)
3-6 is in hot with harpoons.
GUNNER 1: Here we go, baby.
See, we go in from below
where there's gaps in the armor.
GUNNER 1: All right, let's go.
Get up in there.
PILOT 1: I'm goin' in.
GUNNER 1: Get me in close.
(TULKUN CALLS)
Hold her steady.
In range.
Arm one.
GUNNER 1: Arming, target lock.
And one away.
(AIR HISSING)
(TULKUN SQUEALS IN PAIN)
PILOT 2: Two's in hot.
- Arm one.
- GUNNER 2: Arming.
Fire.
- (HISSING)
- (TULKUN GROANS)
- Good strike. Arm two.
- Arming.
Two away.
Booyah!
PILOT 2: Nice.
3-6, you owe us a beer.
(TULKUN CALLING)
You see, the bags slow her down
and keep her up at the surface.
Yeah.
Get on her!
Get me in there.
Straight up on her.
30 meters.
Explosive-tipped harpoon.
Ten meters. Get me in there.
Put me in the pocket.
Now steady, steady.
Stay with her.
Hold. Hold.
Line's runnin'!
(TULKUN SHRIEKS AND MOANS)
Hold on to your ponytail,
Colonel!
Oh. Whoa-ho!
(SOUND CANNON FIRING)
Hold back full!
Back full, aye.
(TULKUN SQUEALS)
Hold her.
(GRUNTS)
She takes an explosive harpoon
to the chest,
and she's still runnin'.
Beautiful.
(WAILING)
Whoo!
(WAILING STOPS)
(MUSIC CRESCENDOING)
(MUSIC ENDS)
(SOMBER MUSIC PLAYING)
(CALF CRYING)
(CREW CHEERS)
(CALF CRIES)
(CALF WAILS)
(STAIRS WHIRRING)
The only way to reach
the gland is from below.
We drill up
through the hard palate
into the brain. And...
(WHIRRING STOPS)
These are highly
intelligent beings.
Probably smarter than us.
Not smarter than me.
(CHUCKLES) That is setting
the bar very low.
Hey, I'm the one
with the harpoon.
Yep.
(WHIRRING)
How do you know?
That they're smarter than us?
More neurons, more pathways.
Not only are they smarter,
they're deeply emotional.
More spiritual.
See, this region here
corresponds with
our emotional centers,
but proportionally
it's much larger.
They have music,
philosophy,
mathematics,
complex language.
Okay.
Here we go.
Show me the money.
So that's what
this is all about?
That's it.
Amrita.
Bad luck for the big guys.
This stuff just happens
to stop human aging. Like...
stops it.
Ounce for ounce
the single most valuable
substance known to man.
This little vial here
is worth like,
80 million.
Think fast!
(SIGHS) Please don't.
(LAUGHING)
It's never funny.
Amrita is what's paying
for everything here
on Pandora now.
Even your research.
Ain't that right, Dr. G?
It's why I drink.
That's all you take?
I mean, you just waste the rest?
Drop the bags.
Let's sink her!
No. Leave the bags.
I want 'em to know it was us.
I charge extra
for bein' used as bait.
(BIRDS SQUAWKING)
(GASPING IN SHOCK)
(BIRD SQUAWKS)
(SOBS)
(SCREAMS)
(GRUNTS)
Her name is Ro'a.
She was my Spirit Sister.
She was a composer of songs.
Much revered.
We would sing together.
She waited many breeding
cycles to have this calf.
The clan were so happy for her.
(CRYING)
What is this, Tonowari?
(SCREAMS) What is this?
(SIGHS)
(SENSOR BEEPING)
My Spirit Sister and her baby
have been murdered
by the Sky People!
(VILLAGERS EXCLAIMING ANGRILY)
TONOWARI:
This war has come to us.
We knew about this hunting
of our tulkun people.
But it was over the horizon,
far away.
Now it is here!
(ALL SNARLING)
JAKE: No, you don't...
You gotta understand
how the Sky People think.
They don't care
about the Great Balance.
MAN: We don't answer
to Sky People!
Listen. Listen to him.
The Sky People
are not gonna stop.
This is only the beginning.
You gotta tell
your tulkun to leave.
You gotta tell them
to go far away!
Leave?
(SCOFFS) You live among us,
and you learn nothing!
We will fight to protect
our brothers and sisters!
No, no, no.
(SNARLING)
If you attack,
if you fight,
then they will destroy you!
They will destroy
everything that you love.
- (ALL SHOUT ANGRILY)
- No!
- You hear my words!
- We will fight! We will fight!
Hear my words!
Stay calm.
- Stay calm!
- (ALL CLAMORING)
Listen to my father.
Damn it!
He speaks the truth.
(CLAMORING DIES DOWN)
You tell the tulkun
that if they're hit
by one of these,
they're marked for death.
(TONOWARI SIGHS)
And call for me,
I'll silence it.
Saving their lives,
that's all that matters.
Right?
Saving your family.
(SOLEMN MUSIC PLAYING)
Tell the tulkun.
- Go.
- (VILLAGERS YIPPING)
Go!
We must fight.
MaJake.
I will not stand and do nothing!
It's a trap.
They want us to hit back.
They're not hunting tulkun.
They're hunting us.
- (CLICKING TONGUE)
- (ILU SQUEAKS)
No way you're rolling
out of here, baby brother.
I have to warn Payakan
about the pingers.
No.
You've gotta keep
your skxawng ass here.
He's outcast.
There's nobody
to warn him but me.
Bro,
why do you always have
to make things so hard?
No.
You mean why can't I be
the perfect son like you?
The perfect little soldier.
Well, I'm not you!
Okay?
I'm not you.
He's my brother.
I'm going.
Oh, he's your brother?
No, I'm your brother.
Lo'ak!
Get off me.
- Come back!
- Come on.
- He's going to Payakan.
- (ILU SQUEAKS)
(ALL YIPPING
AND CLICKING TONGUES)
(ILU CHIRPS)
(BREATHING SHARPLY)
TSIREYA: Come back!
There's Lo'ak! Lo'ak.
Lo'ak!
Lo'ak's going to find Payakan!
Wait up!
(INHALES DEEPLY)
Hold on!
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
- All crews to stations.
- Sound general call.
All right, people. Come on.
Let's make some money!
(ALARM BLARES)
(LO'AK GRUNTS)
- (PAYAKAN SQUEAKS)
- Payakan!
Brother!
TSIREYA: Lo'ak!
Lo'ak!
Wait!
(PAYAKAN WHINES, GROANS)
LO'AK: What is it?
What's wrong?
- (PAYAKAN WHINES)
- (SENSOR BEEPING)
Shit!
Stay calm.
- I got this.
- (WHINES)
(PAYAKAN GRUNTS AND SQUEALS)
- (MENACING MUSIC PLAYING)
- Shit!
(GRUNTS)
Lo'ak!
LO'AK: Bro, come on!
Help me out!
Hurry, the ship's coming!
They're over there!
(LO'AK GRUNTS)
Bro, come on!
- (PAYAKAN SQUEALS)
- Bro.
- Come on, bro.
- Hurry!
Call it in!
Call Dad!
Just go! Do it!
- Just do it.
- TSIREYA: Lo'ak, go! Hurry!
Dad. I mean, Devil Dog.
Do you read me?
Did you see where they went?
LO'AK: It's Eagle Eye,
do you copy?
- They went outside the reef.
- Yeah, Lo'ak.
LO'AK: (PANTING) Dad!
We're with a tulkun
that's under attack.
Killer ship's inbound.
It's about two klicks out.
Who's with you?
LO'AK: It's all of us.
- Aonung and Tsireya too.
- (GASPS)
We're at Three Brothers Rocks.
You get to cover,
and you do not engage.
All right? You hear me?
Do not engage.
We're comin'.
Yes, sir.
It's getting closer!
- NETEYAM: Three, two, pull!
- TSIREYA: Pull!
JAKE: (YIPS)
Kids are under attack!
The kids are under attack.
They were defending a tulkun.
It's your kids too.
The demon ship?
Yes! We gotta go!
Weapons.
Sound the alarm!
(YIPPING)
You should stay back.
I ride!
Come!
(CONCH BLOWS)
(NEYTIRI MIMICS BIRDCALL)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(BREATHES DEEPLY)
(GRUNTS)
(BOTH BREATHING HEAVILY)
(IKRAN SCREECHES)
(ALL YELLING AND ULULATING)
- (GRUNTS)
- (IKRAN SQUAWKS)
(ALL YELLING WAR CRIES)
- (TENSE MUSIC CONTINUES)
- (WEAPONS CLICKING)
Sub teams, hatches close.
Two-minute warning.
(ALL GRUNTING)
NETEYAM: Aonung!
Hurry up! Come on!
Bro, hurry up!
Go, go, go!
Pull! Now!
- TSIREYA: Everybody! Together!
- LO'AK: Pull!
I'll be damned.
Sully's kids.
Let's roll.
Not you.
(WHISTLES) Saddle up.
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
GARVIN: Range is 700 meters.
Pinger signal is good.
(GRUNTS)
Pull, harder!
NETEYAM: Pull!
- (ALL GRUNTING)
- TSIREYA: Pull, harder!
Go!
It's out!
Kiri, it's out!
- KIRI: Go. Tuk, go.
- TSIREYA: Go, everybody!
LO'AK: Come on.
Get out of here!
Go that way!
I'll draw them off.
- LO'AK: Okay.
- Lo'ak, come.
- (NETEYAM YIPS)
- Payakan.
Go, go, dive!
Now, dive!
KIRI: Grab on.
(PAYAKAN MOANS)
(ILU SQUEAKING)
(SENSOR BEEPING)
SCORESBY: Range 300.
Ready depth charges,
and fire, fire, fire.
(ILU CRIES)
QUARITCH: No depth charges.
Scoresby, you copy?
These kids
are worthless to me dead.
Hold your fire.
(SENSOR BEEPING)
QUARITCH: Circle out.
Get a cordon around 'em.
Get your subs in the water.
Sub teams, get wet.
(ENGINES ROARING)
(ILU SQUEAKS)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(SCREECHES)
(ILU SCREECHES)
(TENSE MUSIC CONTINUES)
(ILU SQUEAKING AND CLICKING)
(SENSOR BEEPING)
(ILU SQUEAKING)
Crabs flank right.
Get around on 'em.
(ILU CHIRPS)
GUNNER: Don't lose 'em.
Stay on 'em now.
Planes up. We're goin' in!
GUNNER: Oh, hell yeah!
(ILU SQUEAKS)
(ILU CHIRPS)
(TUK GRUNTS)
(ILU SQUEAKS)
(SENSOR BEEPING)
Tone on lock.
Two away.
(ILU SQUEALS)
(ILU CHIRPS)
(TENSE MUSIC CONTINUES)
(ILU SQUEAKS)
(ENGINE ROARING)
(BOTH GASPING)
Where is Tuk?
Did you see her?
(GASPING)
- (ENGINE HUMMING)
- (PANTING)
(HUMMING STOPS)
(SHRIEKS)
Tuk!
GUNNER: Target in sight.
(ALL GASPING AND PANTING)
It is coming.
We gotta go!
(ALL INHALE DEEPLY)
- (SENSOR BEEPING)
- (TSIREYA GRUNTING)
- Switch net.
- Switching.
Fire.
(BOTH WHIMPERING)
- (IKRAN SQUAWKS)
- LO'AK: Hold on!
- (LO'AK GRUNTS)
- TUK: Let me out!
- Watch out!
- TSIREYA: Tuk, move!
Move your hand!
- TUK: Cut it!
- Hurry, hurry!
- (SPIDER GASPING)
- (GRUNTS)
TROOPER: Hey, kid,
get back here!
(ALL GRUNTING)
PRAGER: Drop the weapon.
- RECOM: Put the weapon down!
- Put it down.
- (SNARLS)
- RECOM: Put it down!
- (LO'AK GRUNTS)
- PRAGER: Stay down.
TROOPER 2: Get him! Get him!
RECOM: Put the weapon down!
Drop it, now!
- Put it down!
- Drop the knife.
- Drop it.
- (YELPS)
SPIDER: Hey! Hey,
what are you doing? Stop!
Stop.
Don't hurt them.
PRAGER: Stop moving.
- LO'AK: Spider!
- Bro, you okay?
- (TUK YELPS)
- Yeah. Great, cuz.
- Never better.
- ZDINARSIK: Down!
ZDINARSIK: Shut your mouth.
PRAGER: Knock it off.
Stay still.
ZDINARSIK: Shut up. Quiet.
Get back to the bridge.
Keep him there!
I'm going, I'm going.
- QUARITCH: Yeah.
- (SNARLING)
I remember you.
Cuff 'em to the rail.
All of 'em.
RECOM: Let's go.
- (TUK SNARLING)
- Let's go. Move!
Over here.
Watch 'em.
They bite.
(TSIREYA GROANS)
PRAGER: Get on your knees.
On 'em.
ZDINARSIK: Give me your hand.
No! (GROWLS)
(GROWLS)
- ZDINARSIK: Now the other.
- No.
(RECOM SHUSHES)
(TUK WHIMPERS)
Be brave.
(VILLAGERS YIPPING)
Na'vi inbound!
- Spread out. Weapons up.
- Dad!
Push left.
Spread out.
Stop.
Stop them.
It's Sully.
300 yards.
They got our kids.
- Your daughter.
- (BOTH SNARLING)
Tuk. Lo'ak.
(GASPING)
Jake, tell your friends
to stand down.
You want your kids back,
you come out alone.
You know better
than to test my resolve.
(GASPS) Lo'ak! No!
(WHISPERS) Fuck!
QUARITCH: I took you
under my wing, Jake.
You betrayed me.
You killed your own.
Good men.
Good women.
I will not hesitate
to execute your kid.
Just wait one.
(BREATHES HEAVILY)
(SIGHS)
Hold here.
They are killers of tulkun.
They must die.
Here. Today.
It's me that they want.
That's what all this
has been about, all right?
The hunting of our tulkun.
The taking of our kids.
You brought this upon us!
You! (BREATHING HEAVILY)
Well, then it's me
that has to do this.
(BREATHES HEAVILY)
QUARITCH:
Offer's fixin' to expire.
What's it gonna be?
Check your fire.
I'm comin' out.
MaJake, what is happening?
MaJake?
(SIGHS)
Stay tense, everybody.
All weapons.
(PAYAKAN CLICKS)
(GRUNTS)
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(PAYAKAN GRUNTS)
Easy shot.
You hit him now, they attack.
Wait till he's on board.
(GROWLS)
(ROARING)
(SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC CONTINUES)
(PAYAKAN GRUNTS)
(MAJESTIC MUSIC RISING)
(MUSIC FLOURISHES)
Payakan!
(PAYAKAN BELLOWS)
(CREWMEN SHOUTING)
No!
(ALL YELPING)
Tuk!
(PAYAKAN GRUNTS)
WAINFLEET:
Open fire. Open fire!
(PAYAKAN SQUEALS)
Brother!
- (CREWMAN 1 SCREAMS)
- (PAYAKAN BELLOWS)
- Come about!
- Comin' about!
Get me around!
Get me a shot!
Go, go!
Look out!
(CREWMAN 2 SHOUTS)
(GRUNTS) Hyah!
(SCREECHES)
(ALL SHOUTING WAR CRIES)
- (PAYAKAN SQUEALS)
- (CREWMEN YELL)
SCORESBY: Get me around!
Go, go, go, go!
Get in there,
get me in range.
Go, go, go.
(CLANGS)
(CREWMEN EXCLAIMING)
(BELLOWS)
WAINFLEET: Down!
Bloody hell!
(ALL SHOUTING WAR CRIES)
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
Open fire! Open fire!
Sully's inbound.
I want eyes on!
All right, let's go.
Saddle up. We're up!
(GRUNTS)
(ENGINE WHINES)
(ULULATES)
(YELLS)
- (SCREECHES)
- (RONAL YELLS)
(SCREAMS)
(GUNFIRE)
- (SKIMWING SCREECHES)
- (SCREAMS)
(GROWLS)
(GRUNTS)
Somebody shoot something!
(SKIMWING YELPS)
(GRUNTS)
BOAT PILOT: Stop!
(SCREAMS)
(GRUNTS)
(YELLS)
(NEYTIRI YIPS)
- (GRUNTING)
- (NEYTIRI GASPING)
(NEYTIRI YELPING)
(YELLS)
(IKRAN SCREECHES)
- (GRUNTS)
- (GUN CLICKS)
(GRUNTS)
(NEYTIRI YELPS, YELLS)
- (GRUNTS)
- (NEYTIRI ULULATES)
(WHISPERS) Oh, shit!
(INHALES DEEPLY)
(GRUNTS)
Get after them. Go!
(SENSOR BEEPING)
Breach!
Masks on!
Masks on! Go!
(GRUNTING)
(YELPING)
(PAYAKAN GRUNTS)
(CREW SCREAMING)
- (ALARM BEEPING)
- (CREW EXCLAIMING)
CREWMAN: Switching feeds.
CAPTAIN: What have we got?
What are we lookin' at?
- (GRUNTS)
- TECH: Hey!
(SPIDER GRUNTING)
Hey! Get this guy!
(GRUNTING)
Get him out of here!
- (SPIDER GRUNTING)
- CAPTAIN: Calm down!
Pull! Pull!
- (CRASHING)
- (ALL GRUNTING)
(ALL YELP)
Go, go, go!
(ALL GRUNTING)
(PANICKED SHOUTING)
- (ALARM BLARING)
- Damage report!
Flooding.
Compartment two and three.
You okay?
(ALL GRUNTING)
(GUNFIRE)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(GRUNTS)
- (SKIMWING SCREECHES)
- (JAKE YELLS)
- (SCREAMS)
- (JAKE ROARS)
- (GASPING)
- (IKRAN SQUEALS)
Port bow!
(PAYAKAN GROANS)
SCORESBY: Hard port!
Open fire!
Get me a shot!
Got ya!
(GRUNTS)
(ALL GRUNTING)
Cut us away!
Not responding!
Get us off the cable!
Who's got the harpoon now?
Back full!
(ALL YELL)
SCORESBY: Reload!
Not the cable, you idiot!
We're dead in the water.
Taking on water. Pumps on.
Man your weapons!
I thought you were
the intelligent species here,
- Scoresby.
- Shut ya cakehole, Garvin.
(LAUGHS)
Where are you?
Cheeky bugger.
You think you're
pretty clever, don't ya?
(PAYAKAN BELLOWS)
(CABLE WHOOSHING)
(CREW SCREAMING)
Get down!
(GRUNTING)
(SCREAMS)
Pumps aren't working.
- Abandon ship! Abandon ship!
- (ALARM BLARING)
- Get him to a boat!
- Yes, sir.
CAPTAIN: Let's go, people!
Let's move! Mask up!
(ALL GRUNTING)
(ILU SQUEALS)
Neteyam!
Hey, baby brother.
Need some help?
Shut up. Come on.
Get us loose.
(GRUNTS) Okay,
get Tuk out of here.
Bro, hurry up!
TSIREYA: Okay. Come on.
Who's the Mighty Warrior?
Come on. Say it.
(LO'AK SIGHS)
- (CHUCKLES) Bro!
- Come on. Let's go.
Lo'ak! (GRUNTS)
They've got Spider.
We've gotta get him.
Come on.
Come on, bro.
We can't leave him.
(GRUNTS IN FRUSTRATION)
(GASPING)
- (SQUAWKS)
- (KIRI YELPS)
Let me go!
(GASPING)
No!
TUK: Look!
- (SQUAWKS)
- (GRUNTING)
(BOTH STRAINING)
Let's go, buttercup.
Get up.
I'm not your buttercup, perv!
We've got to go back for her.
Tuk, wait!
Sullys stick together.
(INHALES DEEPLY)
(URGENT CHATTER)
CREWMAN 1: All right,
we're a go for drop. Let's go.
CREWMAN 2: Wait right there,
guys. Wait. All right.
Clear to drop!
(ALARM BLARING)
Check your mask.
Make sure it's tight.
I'm good, dumbass.
PILOT: Move, move!
Evacuating, people.
Come on. Let's go.
Tuk, this is not a good idea.
Tuk!
(GRUNTING)
(PANTING)
(WHISPERS) Kiri.
- Tuk!
- TUK: Shh.
Cut it here.
Come on.
- (GIRLS SCREAMING)
- No!
- (TSIREYA YELPS)
- (GRUNTS)
ZDINARSIK: I got her.
- (ILU SQUEAKS)
- (GRUNTS)
(ILU CLICKS AND SQUEAKS)
We can still get this done.
Hell yeah.
(WHIMPERS) I can't believe
I'm tied up again!
- (ALARM BLARING)
- TROOPER 1: Hurry up, guys.
TROOPER 2: You want
to go down with this ship?
(GRUNTING)
(PANTING)
- Bro, come on.
- Let's go.
Thanks, guys.
- Go!
- No!
- Bro, come on!
- NETEYAM: Go, go, go!
SPIDER: Go, go, go!
Give me that!
Go, go, go!
This way.
WAINFLEET: Cover, cover!
(GRUNTS)
You see 'em?
- (LAUGHS) Bro!
- (CHUCKLES)
- That was insane, cuz.
- Yeah.
Whoo-hoo!
(GRUNTING)
(COUGHS)
Get on!
Come on, bro!
You skxawng.
I'm shot.
(PAINED GRUNTING)
Shit!
Gimme a hand!
- Keep him up!
- SPIDER: I got him.
Come on.
- Grab him.
- Bro, I got him.
Holy shit.
- Hold him up!
- (SPIDER GRUNTS)
(NETEYAM COUGHS)
- Bro, come on.
- (ILU SQUEALS)
It's okay, bro. I got you.
SPIDER: Hurry. Go, go, go!
They have Kiri and Tuk.
I can't go back.
- Dad!
- (NETEYAM GASPING LABORIOUSLY)
- Dad, help! It's Neteyam!
- (COUGHING)
TSIREYA: Hurry!
LO'AK: Here! Take him.
- Oh, no.
- It's Neteyam! He's hurt!
- SPIDER: Jake.
- Come on. Come on!
Hurry, please!
JAKE: Pull!
(COUGHING)
Bro, watch his head.
Watch his head.
JAKE: Pull!
Come on!
- Just watch his head.
- (NETEYAM GASPING SHALLOWLY)
Okay.
It's okay, bro.
- We got you.
- (NETEYAM COUGHING)
Oh, no.
Put pressure.
Put pressure on it.
(STIFLED GRUNTING)
NETEYAM: Dad, I...
It's okay.
I'm here.
- No, no, no, no, no.
- JAKE: It's okay. I'm here.
- It's okay, son. I gotcha.
- No...
(NETEYAM GASPING LABORIOUSLY)
LO'AK: It's okay.
I want to go home. (GRUNTS)
(NETEYAM GASPING RAPIDLY)
(VOICE QUIVERS)
I know. I know.
It's okay, we're goin' home.
We're goin' home.
It's okay. It's okay.
Dad, I...
(STOPS BREATHING)
Neteyam...
(SIGHS)
No. No, no, no.
Neteyam!
(SCREAMING)
- (JAKE SHUSHING SOFTLY)
- (SOBS) Neteyam.
Oh, Great Mother.
No, Great Mother.
- (LO'AK CRYING)
- (SOBBING) Please.
Oh, my son.
My son.
No!
(NEYTIRI WAILING)
My son!
No!
QUARITCH: (ON COMMS)
Can you hear me, Corporal?
NEYTIRI: No, no, no.
QUARITCH: Yeah, yeah,
I think you can.
I got your daughters.
(NEYTIRI CONTINUES WAILING)
Same deal as before.
You for them.
NEYTIRI: No! (SOBBING)
Where are your sisters?
Your sisters.
Where are they?
I don't know.
- (SHOUTS) Where are they?
- They're on the ship.
They're tied up on the ship.
They're...
They're at the moon pool.
At... At the well deck.
Midships.
What?
Come on. I'll show you.
Come on.
- I'll show you.
- QUARITCH: Talk to me,
Corporal.
- Z, up top.
- I need somethin', Jake,
or there's gonna
be consequences.
Yeah, I hear you.
(BREATHES HEAVILY)
- Come on.
- SPIDER: Come on!
- (NEYTIRI WEEPING)
- Let's go. We gotta go.
Come on, let's go.
- NEYTIRI: No!
- JAKE: Let's go.
- Listen. Listen. Listen to me.
- NEYTIRI: No...
(SCREAMS, SOBS)
Listen to me.
Listen to me. Listen to me.
They have our daughters.
(CONTINUES SOBBING)
I need you with me.
And I need you to be strong.
Right now.
Strong heart.
(NEYTIRI BREATHING HEAVILY)
Yeah.
Let's go get our daughters.
(CONTINUES BREATHING HEAVILY)
(IKRAN SNARLS)
(SCREECHES)
(TSIREYA CRYING)
You stay with your brother.
Dad, I want to go with you.
You've done enough.
Dad... (SIGHS)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
Hold fire.
Let's go.
He's coming.
I'm good. Go, go!
Let's get this guy.
It's what we came here for.
(EXHALING SHARPLY)
(GRUNTS)
Stay with him.
No...
TROOPER:
Heads on a swivel, guys.
(TENSE MUSIC CONTINUES)
Go.
Where are they?
The middle deck.
Where they launch the subs.
There's, like,
a pool in the center.
They're at the forward railing.
No, no.
Stay here.
QUARITCH: (ON COMMS)
Talk to me, Corporal.
This ship's going down
and your girls with it.
Your boy didn't have to die.
You brought that on yourself.
(TROOPERS SPEAKING
INDISTINCTLY)
You thought you could keep
your family safe,
but you can't.
(BOTH BREATHING HEAVILY)
Only one way to keep them safe.
So let's get this over with
before you lose another kid.
- Get down!
- (SPIDER GRUNTS)
(ALL GRUNTING)
(PANICKED SHOUTING)
(PAINED GRUNTING)
- (DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYS)
- (GRUNTING)
(YELLS)
(GRUNTS)
- (TROOPER GASPING)
- (GRUNTS)
WAINFLEET: Who's down?
- Zdinarsik, you copy?
- WAINFLEET: Sound off!
- JAKE: Clear!
- (GRUNTS)
Prager. You read?
TROOPER 2: Eyes up. Eyes up!
(SCREAMS)
(GRUNTS)
Move up!
(YELLS)
Push left. Go!
Push right. Get around on her.
TROOPER 2: Who's got eyes?
(DRAMATIC MUSIC CONTINUES)
(GRUNTING)
(GRUNTS)
TROOPER 2: Move!
(GRUNTING)
(HISSES)
(GRUNTS)
- (BOTH GRUNTING)
- MaJake.
(BOTH GRUNTING)
It's Mom!
(GRUNTS)
KIRI: That's right.
They're coming for you.
(HISSES)
(SNARLING)
(YELLS)
(GRUNTING)
(TROOPER 3 GASPING IN FEAR)
(SCREAMS)
(GROWLING)
(SCREAMING MANIACALLY)
(SNARLING)
(GASPING)
(PANTING)
(SNARLS)
(PANTING RAGGEDLY)
(INHALES)
(PANTING FEARFULLY)
(GRUNTS)
(SOFTLY) Dad! Dad.
(JAKE SHUSHES)
(TUK GRUNTS)
Okay. Where's your sister?
Where is she?
That way.
Okay, stay behind me.
(GRUNTS)
- Kiri!
- (GRUNTS)
QUARITCH: Runnin' out
of time here, Corporal.
You already lost one kid today.
You really wanna lose another?
- (JAKE GRUNTS)
- Do not test me!
(GRUNTS)
- Just kill him, Dad!
- (QUARITCH GRUNTS)
Kiri.
Weapons down.
Don't. Don't do it.
QUARITCH: Down!
Kick 'em away.
Do it!
No.
QUARITCH: Cuff yourself.
No! No, don't hurt her, okay?
- Don't...
- Stand there!
- TUK: (SOFTLY) Don't!
- Don't move!
Not a step.
Cuffs on. Now.
You son of a bitch.
SPIDER: Please,
don't hurt her.
(SNARLS)
Release.
Or I cut.
What, you think I care
about some kid?
He's not mine.
We're not even the same species.
Just please don't...
don't hurt her.
Just please let her go.
- Don't.
- SPIDER: Please!
- KIRI: Don't kill him.
- SPIDER: Listen to me!
Let her go. Don't hurt her.
Mom, don't kill him.
A son for a son.
SPIDER: Please don't hurt her.
(GROANS)
I cut.
Please just let her go, okay?
Just let her go.
- (SCREAMS)
- No!
(KIRI GASPING)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(GRUNTS)
Kiri... Kiri. Kiri.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(PANTING)
(EXHALES)
KIRI: Spider.
Spider, get 'em out of here.
Come on.
Guys. Tuk.
I owe you a death.
(SNARLS)
KIRI: Mom.
- Mama.
- KIRI: Come.
Come on.
- Please, Mama.
- (SNARLS)
You're not leaving,
are you, Jake?
- KIRI: It's okay.
- Knowin' I'm out there.
Knowin' that I'll never stop.
I'm coming for you.
And when I do,
I'll kill your whole family.
Dad...
Then let's get it done.
(GRUNTING)
- Jake!
- (EXPLOSION)
- TUK: It's coming!
- Back. Back.
Get back to the ship. Go!
KIRI: Tuk, swim, swim.
- Stay close.
- SPIDER: Come on.
- Keep moving. Go, go, go!
- Stay close.
-KIRI: Tuk. Tuk
-(SCREAMING)
NEYTIRI: Tuk!
- SPIDER: Grab her!
- Mom, take my hand!
- SPIDER: Hold on!
- KIRI: Hold on!
- (TUK SCREAMS)
- Tuk!
Mom!
KIRI: No!
- Kiri, come on. Kiri...
- No...
- ...we've got to go, come on.
- No!
(GRUNTS) Tuk!
SPIDER: Go!
Climb. Climb!
- Kiri, come on!
- (GRUNTING)
Come on, let's go!
- (PANTING) Mom!
- Swim! Swim.
Go, Tuk.
Climb up.
(TUK GRUNTS)
(BOTH GRUNTING)
- Mom...
- Run!
- (SCREAMS)
- Go!
Go, go, go!
(GRUNTING)
(GROANS)
SPIDER: Keep climbing! Go!
(METAL CREAKS)
I got you.
SPIDER: Give me your hand!
Come on!
- (TUK PANTING)
- NEYTIRI: Okay... Tuk!
- Open it!
- (NEYTIRI GRUNTS)
(BOTH GRUNTING)
- (GRUNTS)
- TUK: Open it!
NEYTIRI: Move back. Move back.
Come.
- Tuk!
- (YELPS)
(NEYTIRI YELPS)
(NEYTIRI GRUNTS)
(BOTH GRUNTING)
Climb!
Come on.
Go!
Go up!
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(METAL CREAKS)
SPIDER: We're rolling over!
- Go, go, go, go!
- Okay...
(METAL GROANS)
(GRUNTS) No!
- (GRUNTS) Mom!
- Tuk.
(METAL CREAKS)
(BOTH GRUNT)
- (GRUNTS)
- Kiri!
Keep going!
(BOTH GRUNTING)
This way, this way!
KIRI: Okay.
NEYTIRI: Go!
(NEYTIRI GRUNTING HEAVILY)
- Open it! Open it!
- (GRUNTS LOUDLY)
Mom!
(BOTH PANTING AND GRUNTING)
SPIDER: Come on!
(BOTH GASPING)
Go, Tuk! (GASPING ANXIOUSLY)
TUK: There's no way out!
Stay together, okay?
- Yes.
- Stay together.
Yes. (INHALES DEEPLY)
(PANTING)
(CHUCKLES)
(GASPING)
(BREATHES SHARPLY)
(INHALES DEEPLY)
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(TENSE MUSIC PLAYING)
Oh, Great Mother!
Oh, Great Mother, help us!
(STRAINING)
(CHOKING)
(BOTH GRUNT)
(TENSE MUSIC INTENSIFIES)
- (JAKE GRUNTING)
- (CHOKING)
(MUSIC TEMPO SLOWING DOWN)
(MUSIC STOPS)
- (GASPING)
- Kiri!
(UNEASY MUSIC PLAYING)
(YIPPING)
SPIDER: Bro!
Mom and Dad are down there.
- In the ship.
- Grab on.
Bro, I'm good. Go!
(GAGGING)
(GAGGING STOPS)
(LOW SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC
PLAYING)
(SQUEAKS)
(HEAVY BREATHING THROUGH MASK)
Okay.
(LOW SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC
CONTINUES)
(GASPS)
Jake!
(HEAVY BREATHING)
(CHAIN RATTLING)
(SPIDER GRUNTS)
(PANTING)
- (GASPS FOR BREATH)
- Dad.
(COUGHS)
(CRACKLY BREATHING)
(SIGHS) Fuck!
(GRUNTS)
(GRUNTING AND PANTING)
Come on, you son of a bitch!
Dad, just breathe.
Neteyam?
No, Dad.
It's Lo'ak.
Oh, Lo'ak.
I'm sorry, sir.
I'm sorry about Neteyam.
It's all my fault.
Just focus.
Focus on now.
- (ELECTRICITY CRACKLES)
- (METALLIC RUMBLING)
(PANTING)
(AIR HISSING)
We're losing the air pocket.
Come on.
We've gotta move.
Come on, Dad.
(PANTING LABORIOUSLY)
You know your way out?
I think so. But, Dad, it's
gonna be a long breath-hold.
I can't make it.
- You can. You can.
- No.
- So you gotta go right now.
(VOICE BREAKING)
I can't lose you too, Dad.
Please.
(METAL RUMBLING)
Mama, I'm scared.
It is all right.
Stay close to me.
- (ELECTRICITY CRACKLING)
- Stay close to Mama.
(BREATH SHUDDERING)
It's okay.
(DREAMY MUSIC PLAYING)
You just have to
slow your heart down.
Be real calm.
Breathe from here.
Hey, breathe from here.
(INHALES DEEPLY)
The way of water
has no beginning and no end.
(BREATHING DEEPLY)
The sea is around you
and in you.
The sea is your home
before your birth
and after your death.
(EXHALES DEEPLY)
The sea gives and the sea takes.
Water connects all things.
Life to death.
(BREATHING SLOWLY)
Darkness to light.
(BOTH GASPING)
(INHALES DEEPLY)
- KIRI: Hi.
- Kiri!
Kiri.
Everything's going to be
all right, little sister.
Mom,
I'm gonna give this to you.
It'll help you.
Dad, you can do this.
(BREATHES DEEPLY)
- Trust me.
- Yeah.
Calm your heart.
Big breaths.
(ALL BREATHING DEEPLY)
Last breath. (INHALES DEEPLY)
(INHALES DEEPLY)
- (TUK INHALES DEEPLY)
- Follow me.
(SOFT MUSIC PLAYING)
(JAKE GAGS)
- (PAYAKAN CLICKS, MOANS)
- (JAKE GAGGING)
(PAYAKAN MOANS)
(BOTH GASPING FOR AIR)
Hold on.
Just breathe.
- Just breathe.
- (BOTH PANTING)
Thank you.
(PAYAKAN TRILLS)
I See you,
son.
MaJake!
- Dad!
- Mom!
Dad. Dad.
Come on.
- Come here.
- KIRI: Tuk.
- LO'AK: I got you.
- Here.
(ALL PANTING IN EXHAUSTION)
Brother.
(SOBS)
(SIGHS DEEPLY)
(BOTH CHUCKLE)
JAKE: Sullys stick together.
It was our greatest weakness
and our great strength.
(SOFTLY) Thank you,
Great Mother.
Thank you.
(SIGHS)
(PAYAKAN TRILLS)
(DRAMATIC DRUMBEATS)
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(GRUNTS IN EXERTION)
(BOTH PANTING)
(HEAVY WINGBEAT)
(SCREECHING)
Let's move out.
Son.
Come with me.
(SNARLS)
Spider! (PANTING)
- (IKRAN GROWLS)
- (GRUNTS)
(SCREECHING)
(TUK CRYING)
(GRUNTING)
(PANTING)
Monkey Boy!
Spider.
(PANTING)
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
- You all right?
- Yeah.
Come here.
JAKE: A son for a son.
(SINGING IN NA'VI)
Every songcord
must have a last bead.
(NEYTIRI CONTINUES
SINGING IN NA'VI)
A father protects.
It's what gives him meaning.
(NEYTIRI CONTINUES
SINGING IN NA'VI)
(SOBS QUIETLY)
(EXHALING SLOWLY)
(INHALES DEEPLY)
The People say that
all energy is only borrowed.
And one day
you have to give it back.
(MOURNFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
Eywa holds
all her children in her heart.
Nothing is ever lost.
Neteyam!
NA'VI PEOPLE: Neteyam!
(MOURNFUL MUSIC CONTINUES)
My family and I,
we'll move on tomorrow.
Far away from here.
Your son lies
with our ancestors.
You are Metkayina now.
JAKE: And there it was.
We are Sea People now.
This is our home.
(WISTFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(PAYAKAN MOANS)
(SOFT CRACKLE)
(WHOOSHING)
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
(ECHOING) Dad!
Look what I caught!
Wow.
Oh, that's a big one.
He was in that pool.
By the rocks.
(GRUNTS)
Right where you said.
(CRIES SOFTLY)
OLDER NETEYAM:
What is it, Dad?
Why are you crying?
(SOFTLY) I'm just happy
to see you, boy.
I'm happy to see you, too.
(CHUCKLES)
Here.
You try.
Okay.
Leave any for me?
- Uh, maybe.
- (CHUCKLES)
(ARROW SHOOTS)
JAKE: (CHUCKLES)
Yeah! Check that out. See?
(WISTFUL MUSIC CONTINUES)
I see now.
I can't save my family
by running.
This is our home.
This is our fortress.
This is where we make our stand.
(DRAMATIC DRUMBEATS)
(NOTHING IS LOST (YOU GIVE ME
STRENGTH) BY THE WEEKND PLAYS)
(WISTFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(BLISSFUL MUSIC PLAYING)
(THE SONGCORD BY ZOE SALDAÃ‘A
PLAYING)
(ZOE SALDAÃ‘A SINGING IN NA'VI)